Today's דף daf *daf* is נ"ו *Nun Vav*, fifty-two. We pick up
on the bottom of נ"א עמוד ב' Amud Beis, *Nun Aleph Amud
Bet* and we are dealing with again this whole issue of רקב
*rekev* of the dust that from a decomposed dead body and that
it causes טומאה tuma, *tumah* only under very narrowly defined circumstances,
primarily a naked body in a marble casket plus any other circumstances
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* might have put on top of that
other criteria. Anyway, we pick up on the bottom of נ"א עמוד
ב' amud beis *Nun Aleph Amud Bet* and three lines from the
bottom, last word on the line. בעי רבא Rava *Bei Rava*, רבא
Rava *Rava* asked the following question. נמלה שחסרה *Nemalah shechasrah*, if you
have an ant that is missing, that is not whole, because we
discussed before whether there is רקב *rekev* that comes from a body
that is not whole and other very arbitrary
exclusions of certain laws from certain laws of a body that's not
whole, this whole idea that if you find it buried in the
ground in a place where it doesn't belong you have to take
the dirt with it, you have to be concerned that there's a
graveyard there, that was very strange, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* said maybe this
seems completely arbitrary. But anyway we had just gotten through discussing certain
limits to in cases where the body is not whole. So now
we're going to ask about other non-human bodies that are not whole.
If you have an ant that is not whole, let's say it's
missing a leg, okay, and it can still survive and it's still
viable, okay, so מהו *mahu*, what's the הלכה Halacha *halacha*? Because the
הלכה Halacha *halacha* is that if you eat a whole ant although
normally the שיעור shiur. *shiur* is a כזית kezayit *kezayit* for eating
something to get lashes, if you eat a whole bug that is
biblically prohibited even if it is less than a כזית k'zayis. *kezayit*,
you still get lashes, that's the concept of בריה birya *biryah*, that
something of significance that it's an entire ant that you ate, so
therefore that is a significant act even if it's less quantitatively then
it makes up qualitatively what it lacks quantitatively. So let's say you
ate an ant that was missing a leg, okay, would you still
get lashes?
So מהו *mahu*, they're going into now it is a כשרות *kashrut*
question and not a טומאה tuma, *tumah* question?
Yes, but we're
going in terms of like what it would have been like if
it's missing a leg, what happens if you touch the leg?
No, okay, but because the law of בריה birya. *biryah* only applies
to eat, to the prohibition of eating not to the שיעור shiur
*shiur* for טומאה tuma.
*tumah*. I just wonder if it's alive or dead then.
Correct. But let's, but yes. But you might say that if the
missing limb is something that would make it not viable then it's
taken for granted that it's no longer has the status of a
בריה birya *biryah*, but if it's something that it still could be
viable, okay, so what's the story? מהו *mahu*, שיעורא גמרינן ליה והחסר
*shiura gmarina lei vehachasar*, is there a concept of שיעור shiur *shiur*,
meaning even though it seems like what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
asking is that even though we say that if it's an entity,
a בריה birya *biryah*, you don't need a quantitative amount defined by
a כזית k'zayis, *kezayit*, nevertheless what we do say is that in
the end it gets translated into a quantitative amount. So you look
at a whole ant and you say okay, so for this ant
the minimum size is whatever the volume is of this whole ant.
In the end it gets translated into a quantitative amount and then
okay, so now you don't have the whole ant, it's missing, it's
not the full שיעור shiur *shiur*, או בריה birya גמרינן ליה *o
biryah gmarina lei*, or do we never translate it into a quantitative
amount? We say if something is like a live, if it's a
viable entity and it's an entire entity, you know, and maybe ואיכא
*ve'ika*, you could say that even though it's not, doesn't have this
leg, it's still considered a בריה birya *biryah*, still considered an entity,
you know, so it never gets translated and therefore missing a little
bit could still have that qualitative significance of בריה birya *biryah*. That's
the question. אמר רב Rav יהודה מדסקרתא *Amar Rav Yehuda miDiskharta*,
תא שמע Ta shema, *ta shema*, come and hear, top of נ"ב
עמוד א' Amud Aleph. *Nun Bet Amud Aleph*. בהם *bahem*, so this
is now we go back to here we go Rabbi we go
back to
טומאה tuma *tumah*, okay, so this is a question about a שרץ
sheretz, *sheretz* that causes טומאה tuma *tumah* like a dead rodent and
it says כל kol אשר יגע בהם *kol asher yiga bahem*, if
you touch them you become טמא tamei. *tamei*, and another פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says כל kol אשר יפול מהם *kol asher yipol mehem*, if
something from them falls into something it makes it טמא tamei. *tamei*.
So the difference is בהם *bahem* seems to mean the entire thing,
okay, you touch them. No, מהם *mehem* means something from it, בהם
*bahem* seems to mean you touch the thing itself, the entirety. So
תא שמע ta shema. *ta shema*, בהם יכול בכולן *bahem yakhol bekulan*,
maybe you have to touch the thing has to be in its
entirety, תלמוד לומר מהם *talmud lomar mehem*, from them. אם מהם *im
mehem*, if it's from them, יכול מקצתן *yakhol miktzatan* even a little
bit of it, תלמוד לומר בהם *talmud lomar bahem*, the entire thing.
הא כיצד *ha keitzad*, how do you get something that's both satisfies
the idea of entire and partial? עד ad, שיגע במקצתן שהוא ככולן
*ad sheyiga bemiktzatan shehu kekulan*, it's enough to touch a little bit
of a rodent but that it's something that somehow is representative of
an entire one. How is that? How is it representative? ושיערו חכמים
Chachamim כעדשה ke'adasha *veshi'eru hachamim kekhadashah*. So here it's not a concept
of בריה birya *biryah* because you never look rodent by rodent, but
you basically say look the smallest size rodent that you ever will
have will be the size of a lentil bean, why is that?
שכן החומט תחלת ברייתו כעדשה ke'adasha *shekein hachomet techilat briato kekhadashah*. Skink.
What's a
skink? It's a
lizard kind of thing.
There's
a picture of it.
Yeah, so what does it look like?
It's a worm, no?
Like a worm type of thing.
It's an amphibian.
All right, whatever.
What are their two possibilities?
Snail or or a type of lizard.
Snail or lizard. Okay. Anyway, this חומט, hachomet which is one of
the things that causes טומאה, tuma, it's when it's initially formed, meaning
apparently but when it just hatches or however it's born, it is
the size of a lentil bean. So therefore we sort of put
all of the שרצים shratzim in the in the same category and
we say that something, the smallest quantity that represents an entire שרץ,
sheretz is the smallest size of the smallest שרץ sheretz? when it
is just born and that would be a size of a lentil
bean. Okay? And that's מקצתן שהוא ככולן, miktzatan shehu kechulan, it represents
an entire one.
What? An ant is not a שרץ?
sheretz An ant is not a שרץ sheretz for טומאה, tuma okay,
it's אסור assur for eating, it's not a שרץ sheretz. for טומאה.
tuma Even
an ant is even smaller. Even whole. Okay, that's true, but let's
see what the גמרא Gemara, is going to do with this. שמע
מינה, Shema mina, now that's a טומאה tuma question and again, the
idea of בריה which is case by case and never doesn't apply
by these שרצים shratzim in the end of the day for this
טומאה הלכה tuma halacha you have, you end up with just a
quantitative number.
If you have a piece of a dead mouse, then unless
it's the size of a lentil bean, you're not טמא.
tamei In the size of a lentil bean, but just not from
a whole limb and not anything, just a little piece of flesh?
Right, you're טמא. tamei Yeah, sure. Like a כזית k'zayis of a
corpse is a כעדשה ke'adasha? of a שרץ. sheretz Okay, that's the
amount of flesh of a שרץ and this is where we get
it from. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה שיעורא
גמירי לה. Shema mina shiura gemiri lah. So you see that it's
a question of שיעורין shiurin not a question of בריה. Now how
you get that is unclear. It seems that, meaning that's a טומאה
tuma question, but it seems that the point of the גמרא, Gemara
what does it have to do with the definition of a בריה
for eating? But it seems that the point of the גמרא Gemara
is is that even if our way we start with a concept
of something that represents etc., in the end of the day we
want to get to a number, we want to quantify it. That's
what we did over there and then we made it a כעדשה
ke'adasha for everything. So therefore here too, even though again it's different
because it's case by case, if you have big ant, small ant,
each בריה is defined by is it the whole of the ant
you have in front of you, nevertheless it's sort of saying we
want to end up with a quantity, with a number. So therefore
it would be the size of that ant and anything less than
that size you don't sort of say anything less than that size
would not be complete. Seems like that's the point, that in the
end we try to translate it into a quantity. Now תוספות Tosafot
learns this a little differently, how the גמרא Gemara, learns this out
and תוספות Tosafot. says like
this: two lines down in the narrow lines from the top of
the דף Daf. here in תוספות. Tosafot He says like this: בשלמא
שיעורא גמירי מדבעינן כעדשה, Bishlama shiura gemiri midba'inan ke'adasha, since you need
a size of a lentil bean, שהרי החומט
גם כי הוי תחילתו כעדשה היו לו רגליו
וקרניו, sheharei hachomet gam ki havei techilato ke'adasha hayu lo raglav vekarnav,
that when you how did you get to the size of a
lentil bean? That was an entire חומט hachomet with its legs and
its horns. Okay, ובכל מקום יחתוך ממנו פורתא דמיבצר מכעדשה אפילו הכי
חיה, uvechol makom yachtoch mimeno purta demivtzar mike'adasha afilu hachi chaya, but
you could have cut a little piece of the חומט hachomet and
maybe it would have been missing a leg and it still would
have survived, ואפילו הכי בעינן כעדשה ממש כביאתה, ve'afilu hachi ba'inan ke'adasha
mamash keviyata, but nevertheless when we translated it into a quantitative amount
we don't say how much what's the size of a חומט hachomet.
that could have lived, a baby חומט. hachomet. We say what is
the full size of a חומט. hachomet ושמע מינה שיעורא גמירי. Ushma
mina shiura gemiri. Okay, so you see that it's a שיעור. shiur
So again תוספות Tosafot sort of says the point is that since
we learn out from the size of a full one and not
from one lacking a leg, that shows you that we need something
that is full. I would say I think I would I'm sort
of just say conceptually I would more emphasize the conceptual point here.
You see we're trying to translate it into a quantity and therefore
not assess the
בריה question contextually or on a case or on a more qualitative
basis. Okay, so that's the proof. Now the גמרא Gemara isn't done.
אמר רב שמעיה, Amar Rav Shemaya, back to the גמרא, Gemara כי
בעינן שיעורא, Ki ba'inan shiura, no no no. When do we need
a שיעור shiur in this case of the חומט hachomet and of
the כעדשה? k'adasha, דבלאו הכי כעדשה לא מטמא דלא נפלה ביה נשמה,
Devalo hachi ke'adasha lo metamei dela nafla beh neshama, because if it
wasn't the size of a כעדשה k'adasha, of a lentil bean it
would not become טמא tamei why? Because it had not yet had
a soul enter into it. אבל נפלה ביה נשמה, Aval nafla beh
neshama, once the soul has entered into it, לא תיבעי
לך,
lo tibaya
lach, you wouldn't need it. So the thing can anything alive is
smaller?
What does that mean? That's very unclear what that means. What תוספות
Tosfos says that means is is that even though it's true that
an animal could be missing a leg or somehow and survive, that's
only after it's been born, but if this little baby חומט chomet
was born and somebody had sort of torn off the leg or
it was born without that leg it would be born smaller... smaller
than the size of a כעדשה, it would not have been big
enough to be viable. Okay, so the reason that we are not
considering a size smaller than a כעדשה, a size of a baby
חומט without a leg, is such a thing is not viable. But
if somebody goes ahead and eats an ant that has been walking
around and living and with an and a leg that's been torn
off, which is viable, that still remains a question whether we would
consider that a בריה or not.
נפשא בנשמה Nafsha baneshama means it is viable? No.
נפשא בנשמה Nafsha baneshama means that the soul has entered into it.
So because since a soul has yet to enter into it, it's
not מטמא metame because it's not viable. But once the soul has
entered into it and then it loses a limb, that's why תוספות
Tosafot is saying it remains viable. Okay, so it's a little hard
to understand what the גמרא Gemara is really getting at because but
it seems like again the point is that בריה considers is a
qualitative substitute for the quantitative significance of a כזית. Actually it's funny
to say it that way because most people normally ask the other
way. They say like what's the reason that you need a certain
quantitative amount? If you ate a טריפה treif food, you ate a
טריפה treif food, right? And you have to say well only when
you've done a certain quantitative amount is it an act of some
qualitative significance, right? So normally you need the quantitative amount to give
a qualitative significance. But here what we're saying is once we start
with an idea of כזית, בריה is a substitute for that, and
it seems that the גמרא's Gemara question is is it always that
we just ask the question is this a whole entity? Or that
in the end the whole entity gets translated into a quantitative measure
and then even the smallest lacking of that, again it would be
funny because it would be different case by case, every single ant
you give a different number. Yes, Charlie.
It says snakes don't have limbs at all and there's species of
skinks that don't have limbs at all.
Okay, so I don't know what to say. So that shows that
it's not a skink. Okay, now we move on, thankfully. Okay, השדרה
והגולגולת. Hashidra vehagulgoles. I mean we're still dealing with body parts, but
it's a little bit different than what we dealt with yesterday. Okay,
השדרה והגולגולת, Hashidra vehagulgoles, the skull and the spinal cord
are remember bone, the smallest amount is a causes טומאה, tuma causes
טומאת מת tumas meis if you touch it, okay,
and it's the size of a barley bean and bone but you
need enough bones that represent more of the whole body to cause
טומאה באוהל. tuma beohel. That's one of the major things which is
מטמא metame like most of these cases, a כזית of flesh, these
other types of things, it's the same size for טומאה tuma in
touch and טומאה tumah, in an אוהל. ohel. Bone is the major
thing that's different, right? A tiny bit of barley size bean size
of grain, excuse me, of of bone causes טומאה tumah. by touch,
but until it causes טומאה באוהל tuma beohel you need enough that
sort of represents the whole body. How much is this? So there
basically two שיעורים. shiurim. One is רוב בנינו rov binyano or רוב
מנינו, rov minyano, the majority of the numbers of bones or of
the structure of the body, and even if you don't have all
of those but if you have a רובע rova or חצי קב,
chatzi kav, a quarter or half קב kav of bones coming from
that collection of bones, that causes טומאת אוהל tumas ohel and the
other amount and the other way of the other sort of measure
of bones that causes טומאת אוהל tumas ohel is the skull and
the spinal cord. So what we're going to discuss is it the
skull and the spinal cord or the skull or the spinal cord?
So let's take a look.
I don't care I'm sorry regarding the skull and we don't care
how big this or little the skull or spinal.
Correct, if it's an entire skull we don't care although there we
will get into some related discussion about
that but unlike what we were saying before.
Right, when it comes to the רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב
בנין rov binyan there has to be a quantitative amount. If you
have an entire רוב מנין rov minyan and רוב בנין rov binyan
less than a רובע rova or חצי קב, chatzi kav, like by
a baby or whatever, but the גמרא Gemara sounded before like you
always need the חצי קב. chatzi kav. Okay, so let's take a
look. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they raised the following question. שדרה וגולגולת
תנן, Shidra vegulgoles tenan, is it a spinal cord and the skull,
או דילמא או שדרה או גולגולת, odilma o shidra o gulgoles, or
does it mean either a spinal cord or the skull. Now it's
not a question of what the words are in the משנה, Mishnah,
but it's a classic problem that sometimes the ו vav in Hebrew
means or and sometimes it means and. So what is meant here?
אמר רבא תא שמע, Amar Rava tasha, come and hear. שדרה שגירר
רוב עילעין שבה, Shidra shegirer rov ila'in sheba, if you have a
spinal cord that most of the עילעין ila'in which are the ribs
have been broken, broken off, טהורה. tehora. It's טהור, tahor, it does
not cause טומאה tumah, in an אוהל. ohel. I mean again always
touching is a problem but it doesn't cause טומאה tumah, in an
אוהל. ohel. ובקבר, Uvakever, but if it is in a קבר, kever,
if it's in a you know coffin, אפילו
משוברת או מפורקת טמאה. afilu meshuberes o meforekes temea. Even if it
is broken into pieces, crushed or dismembered, it's still טמאה temea מפני
הקבר, mipnei hakever, because of the קבר. kever. So here's a special
הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, pretty much all this stuff by
טומאה tumah. הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. Okay you just take
that for granted, that that being in the קבר, kever, the קבר
kever is seen as combining it and treating it as if it's
not broken, as it's one object. Okay but that starts with the
idea that if it's broken it's a problem, right? Who ever told
us that if it was broken it was a problem, right? When
you have the bones רוב מנין rov minyan רוב בנין rov binyan
it doesn't matter if they're
broken. that if it's not a whole spinal cord, if the ribs
are most of the ribs are broken off, it's not מטמא, metamei,
but then the חידוש Chiddush number two is, but if they're in
a grave, the grave deals somehow solves that problem and makes it
considered one unit and it is מטמא. metamei. Okay, so that's the
הלכה halachah. of the spinal cord. Now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says about this. It says, טעמא משום דגירי. Ta'ama mishum degirei.
The reason is that it's a problem is because the ribs are
broken off. הא לא גירי טמא. Ha lo girei tamei. If not,
it would be טמא tamei and it sounds like just the spinal
cord itself with the ribs causes טומאה, tumah the only thing we're
talking about, right? So it sounds like that alone causes טומאה. tumah
שמע מינה או שדרה או גולגולת קתני.
Shema mina o shidra
o gulgoleth katani. So the גמרא Gemara says you see that it's
either one or the other. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הלא
קתני. Halo katani. We didn't say exact, exact. We didn't say that
that by itself. הא קמשמע לן, Ha kamashma lan, maybe what it's
really telling me is דכי גירי טהרה איצטריכא לך. dechi girei tahara
itztreicha lach. Look, what it's telling me is when the ribs are
broken off, then you know that you're not going to have a
problem, right? Whether it's the spinal cord and the skull or just
the spinal cord, the whole thing is not טמא tamei. when the
ribs are broken off, right? Because even if you need both, once
the spinal cord this now no longer functions as the spinal cord.
Okay, if you have the ribs on, then yes, it causes טומאה,
tumah but maybe alone, but maybe with the skull. It's not clear,
right? It's telling you that a spinal cord is only defined as
a spinal cord when it has the majority of the ribs. It
is not telling you whether you need just the spinal, whether just
the spinal cord suffices or it's the spinal cord combined with the
skull.
Okay, yeah, just
to be clear,
when
I say spinal cord, I actually mean the column, right? The spinal
column, yeah. Because if you just touch the no, no, I meant
the spinal column, right. Okay, so yes, the right. Okay, so the
backbone really is really a better way to say it. Okay, so
yes, thank you, I'll start saying the backbone. All right, so the
backbone. All right, where were we? Okay, איצטריכא לך. itztreicha lach. So
we don't know. Yes, that's a necessary part of what makes the
backbone considered a backbone, but it is not saying that that does
it by itself necessarily. תא שמע, tashma, come in here. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, שישה דברים רבי עקיבא מטמא וחכמים מטהרים.
Shisha devarim Rabbi Akiva metamei vechachamim mitaherin. There were six things, and
they're all very similar, that Rabbi Akiva said would be טמא tamei.
and the חכמים Chachamim would say were טהור tahor by טומאת מת.
tumat meit. וחזר בו רבי עקיבא, Vechazar bo Rabbi Akiva, and Rabbi
Akiva wound up eventually reversing himself, which is interesting, you don't you
rarely see Rabbi Akiva reverse himself.
ומעשה שהביאו קופות מלאות עצמות לבית הכנסת של טרסיים Uma'aseh shehevi'u kupot
mele'ot atzamot leveit haknesset shel tarsiyim of
metalworkers
or copper workers, והניחו באוויר, vehenichu ba'avir, and they put it out
in the open courtyard because they don't want to bring it into
the בית כנסת, beit knesset, they needed to inspect it, but if
you bring it into the בית כנסת, beit knesset, then all the
כהנים kohanim are טמא. tamay So they put it out in the
open air. But, which is fascinating by the way, the whole issue
about a בית כנסת beit knesset serving as a type of a,
you know, as a בית עם, beit am, as a like a
community place, a gathering place, and not just a בית תפילה, beit
tefillah, that's a בית כנסת, beit knesset, right, to gather, exactly. So
that goes way back to the תנאי tannai period that the rabbis,
you know, tend to not like the idea that they use it
for other functions other than just דאוונען, davening, but that was obviously
a major role that the בית כנסת beit knesset played. Anyway, so
that's where you find people, it's in the שול. shul. Okay, so
they brought it anyway to the בית כנסת beit knesset and they
put it out in the open
air, ונכנס תודוס הרופא. venichnas Thodus Harofeh. The Thodus doctor, he comes
up a lot. וכל הרופאים עמו. Vechol harofim imo. He came with
all the doctors. Okay, so you wonder why they brought it to
the smelting בית כנסת beit knesset and not the doctors' בית כנסת.
beit knesset. Anyway,
ואמרו, ve'amru, and they inspected the box and they said, אין כאן
שדרה ממת אחד. Ein kan shidra mimeit echad. You do not have
here a backbone coming from just one dead body. Okay, and again,
the point being and as we're going to see is that the
debate between Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים Chachamim is what if you
have the minimum quantity for טומאה, tumah. whatever it is, of bones,
of flesh, of blood, but only but coming from more than one
body. Does it all have to come from only one corpse? So
they said, look, you might have, you know, enough bones here to
make a spinal to make a backbone, but it's not all from
the same body. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara so therefore, that's what
they
said, דלא שדרה ממת אחד. dela shidra mimeit echad. טעמא דליכא שדרה
מחדא. Ta'ama deleka shidra michada. So you see the reason it was
טהור tahor and anyway that's relevant to the debate to Rabbi Akiva's
position because Rabbi Akiva said you don't need to be one body.
We're going to quote that whole משנה mishnah in a minute. Okay,
but for now we're saying or it's a ברייתא, braita, excuse me.
But anyway, but for now we're saying, look, presumably if they had
found one backbone from one body, everyone would have agreed it would
have been טמא. tamei טעמא דליכא שדרה מחדא, Ta'ama deleka shidra michada,
from one body. הא איכא או שדרה או גולגולת מחדא. Ha ika
o shidra o gulgoleth michada. If it was enough, one backbone or
one skull from one body, דנזיר מגלח עליה denazir megale'ach aleha would
have been enough for a נזיר nazir to shave and for it
to cause טומאה באוהל. tumah be'ohel. שמע מינה או שדרה או גולגולת.
Shema mina o shidra o gulgoleth. Now it seems like it's or
either. backbone or a skull because all they're discussing is is there
enough of a backbone here? So it says, לא מבעיא קאמר, lo
mibaya ka'amar, it goes without saying. לא מבעיא שדרה וגולגולת דממת חדא
ליכא. lo mibaya shidra ve-gulgollet de-mi-mes chada leka. Look, there wasn't, not
only was there not a skull and backbone from the same corpse,
there wasn't even a backbone from the same corpse. Okay, דממת חדא
ליכא, de-mi-mes chada leka, אלא אפילו או שדרה ממת אחד או
גולגולת ממת אחד ליכא. ella afillu o shidra mi-mes echad o gulgollet
mi-mes echad leka. There wasn't even either, even just once, even the
skull alone from one body or the backbone alone from one body.
Okay, they didn't have anything about it. Again, the simple sense of
all these ברייתות braisos is what the גמרא Gemara initially thought. Right?
Since it's all talking about here's what you need for a backbone
to be מטמא. metamei. Could they find a backbone from one body
or not? And there's no mention of a skull. Certainly it sounds
like that alone does it. But the גמרא Gemara is just saying,
no, maybe you needed that plus the skull, but we're just talking
about the reality status of the backbone. Okay, תא שמע. tashma. Let's
try again. ממנין, mi-minyan, from, if we actually have a number that
that will help us identify how many cases we're talking about. Where's
our number? ומה הן ששה דברים? u-ma hen shisha devarim? Now we're
quoting the end of that ברייתא braisa that we quoted above. What
are the six things שרבי עקיבא מטמא וחכמים מטהרין? she-Rabbi Akiva metamei
ve-Chachamim metaherin? That רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said מטמא tamay and the
חכמים Chachamim said are טהור. tahor. על אבר מן המת שבא משני
מתים. al ever min ha-mes she-ba mi-shnei mesim. You have a limb
that is actually like from two separate bodies. So you know, you
have the bottom of the finger from one and the top of
the finger from another. Okay, that seems like that's obvious and everybody
should say that's טהור tahor even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because the
concept of a limb, right, it's not a quantity, again, like it
would seem like it's something that's really one whole limb that it's
in that it has its initial integrity as as an entity. But
anyway, even that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said would cause טומאה. tumah
ועל אבר מן החי
שבא משני בני אדם, ve-al ever min ha-chai she-ba mi-shnei bnei adam,
or similarly a limb from a living person from two separate living
people. Okay, so if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says even that causes
טומאה tumah, from two separate people, certainly the next cases. ועל חצי
קב עצמות שבא משני מתים. ve-al chatzi kav atzamot she-ba mi-shnei mesim.
Then now when you get to more things that are quantitative quantities.
A half קב kav of bones that comes from two separate corpses.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says טמא tamei and the חכמים chachamim, say
are טהור. tahor. Okay, ועל רביעית דם הבאה משנים, ve-al reviet dam
ha-ba'ah mi-shnayim, and a רביעית reviet of a לוג log of blood,
which is like three ounces, that comes from two corpses. Now again,
the רביעית reviet is only, by, to remind you, it's a little
funny. תוספות Tosafot points this out because the חצי קב עצמות, chatzi
kav atzamot, if you remember, the two main areas so far that
we have found that is a difference between טומאה tumah. and a
נזיר מגלח nazir megaleyach is that טומאה tumah. is is is רביעית
קב עצמות reviet kav atzamot
and רביעית לוג דם reviet log dam
and נזיר מגלח nazir megaleyach
is
חצי קב chatzi kav
and
חצי לוג. chatzi log. Okay, so that's actually so far those are
the base the two places that we have found a difference between
what causes טומאת מת tumat mes and what a נזיר nazir is
מגלח. megaleyach. So this משנה Mishna is actually ברייתא's braisa a little
funny because first it talks about a חצי קב עצמות chatzi kav
atzamot and then it talks about a רביעית דם. reviet dam. Okay,
so the חצי קב chatzi kav is for נזיר מגלח, nazir megaleyach,
the רביעית דם reviet dam is for טומאה. tumah It's a little
funny. But either way, the point is that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says when it comes to the quantity of blood, you can combine
it from two separate dead bodies. Okay, so that's how many are
people keeping track? How many is that so far? Four. אבר מן
המת, Ever min ha-mes, אבר מן החי, ever min ha-chai,
bones, blood, that's
four. ועל עצם כשעורה שנחלק לשנים. ve-al etzem k-se'orah she-nechelak li-shnayim. This
is the one thing that's a little different. It's not from separate
bodies. A piece of bone the size of a of a grain
of barley that has been divided into two. Right? That's something that's
not טומאת אהל, tumat ohel, that's טומאה tumah. by touch. And that
you can also understand. It's so tiny that maybe if it's divided
into two, you know, it becomes it loses any significance even if
they're now put close to each other and touching again. Okay, so
that's five. והשדרה והגולגולת, ve-ha-shidra ve-ha-gulgollet, and the skull and the backbone.
Okay now, again, why why they debating the skull and the backbone?
Implicitly it means the skull and the backbone that come from two
separate bodies. Okay, and that's when you have that story of דוסתאי
הרופא Dustai HaRofei and they said there's no backbone here from one
body. Okay so now, so we're up to we had five and
then we mentioned skull and backbone. So that sounds like it's the
combination. That would make six cases. Okay.
And דם dam and עצם etzem are two.
דם Dam and עצם etzem were two. What do you mean were
counting them? We had אבר מן המת, ever min ha-mes, אבר מן
החי, ever min ha-chai,
bones, blood, a bone that's split into two, and שדרה וגולגולת. shidra
ve-gulgollet.
Yeah, but אבר ever is all one case.
All right, so let's see. So you can imagine a lot of
ways we can we can boil it down which is what the
גמרא's Gemara going to do. Is there a tissue or a napkin
somewhere? Thank you.
All right. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי סלקא דעתך או שדרה
או גולגולת, ve-i salka dachtech o shidra o gulgollet, if you think
it means either one or the other, הני שבע הוו, hani sheva
havvu, that's seven. So the גמרא Gemara now has a lot of
answers to this. Okay. כי קתני כל היכא דפליגי עליה רבים. ki
katani kol heika de-palgi alei rabbim. First of all, no, when we
said six, we meant even though we list... We did list seven,
but six of them are ones in which the חכמים, chachamim many
חכמים chachamim argue on רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. לאפוקי עצם כשעורה, l'afukei
etzem kasiora, the one of those things anyway that didn't belong was
the, you know, one of these things is not like the other
was the piece of bone that was the size of the barley
because that actually was a case where it wasn't from two separate
bodies, it was from dividing something into two. And also, it was
a טומאת מגע tumas maga as opposed to a טומאת אוהל. tumas
ohel. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says that one we're not counting,
but not for the reasons I just gave just because it wasn't
somatically similar, but because also there you don't have the חכמים chachamim
arguing on him, you only have a single opinion arguing on him.
דתני detani one minute, דתני detani we taught a ברייתא, baraita, right,
we list a number we don't mean it. Okay,
ועצם כשעורה שנחלק לשנים ve-etzem k'se'ora shenechlak l'shtayim if it's divided into
two, רבי עקיבא מטמא ורבי יוחנן בן נורי מטהר. Rabbi Akiva metamei
ve-Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri metaher. It's only רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri who disagrees with him. Because again, the major debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים chachamim is not about
something that splits into two, it's something that comes from two separate
bodies. Okay, so that's really his debates with the חכמים Chachamim in
the other six are all from two separate bodies and those are
the six that we're counting, which actually makes a lot of sense.
ואיבעית אימא, ve-ima'iseyma, if you want you could say, ואיבעית
אימא,
ve-ima'iseyma,
כי תני איבר מן המת איבר מן החי לא קתני. ki tani
eiver min hamet eiver min hachai lo ktani. Okay, yeah, we're talking
about, we listed seven, but there are six debates in things that
relate to corpses. The איבר מן החי eiver min hachai we weren't
counting.
ואיבעית אימא,
ve-ima'iseyma, although we've already learned these words, yes they're still debating it
but it wasn't part of our number. And also maybe it's איבר
מן המת, eiver min hamet, איבר מן החי eiver min hachai are
somewhat similar, so we were just sort of putting it in parentheses
together with איבר מן המת. eiver min hamet. ואיבעית אימא, ve-ima'iseyma, if
you want you could say, כי תני כל היכא דנזיר מגלח על
אכילה. ki tani kol heicha denazir migale'ach al achila. No, we're only
talking about things that actually cause טומאת אוהל tumas ohel and and
also mentions נזיר מגלח. nazir migale'ach. Why it says רביעית דם revi'is
dam is is a question. But לאפוקי עצם כשעורה דלא, l'afukei etzem
k'se'ora d'lo, עצם כשעורה etzem k'se'ora is a different type of a
טומאה, tumah it's טומאת מגע, tumas maga, not טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel.
ואיבעית אימא, ve-ima'iseyma, if you want you could say, כי תני כל
היכא דהדר ביה. ki tani kol heicha de-hadar beih. No, no, when
we're talking about six things he debated, we're talking about six he
debated and eventually he reversed himself. Okay, right, because it said וחזר
בו רבי עקיבא. v'chazar bo Rabbi Akiva. But of, we did list
seven, שד וגולגולת shed ve-gulgola are separate, we did list seven, but
but because of of those seven he only reversed himself on six.
Okay, which one did he not reverse himself on? לאפוקי רביעית דם
דלא הדר ביה. l'afukei revi'is dam d'lo hadar beih. The רביעית דם
revi'is dam he did not reverse himself on. Okay, that he continued
to insist is is טמא tamei. even if it comes from two
separate bodies. And by the way, you could understand it because it's
the one that has least distinctive characteristics, right? The bones or whatever
that come from different bodies, you know, תודוס הרופא Todos Harofei was
able to look at the bones and identify that they were from
different bodies. Right, but the blood, I mean before you could do
blood typing or whatever, you know, you couldn't tell. It was all
naturally combined into one unit. And that he did not reverse himself
on. Okay, דאמר
ליה רבי לבר קפרא, de'amar lei Rebbi l'Bar Kappara, so רבי Rebbi
said to בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, לא תשנה רביעית דם בחזרה, lo
tish'na revi'is dam be-chazara, don't list רביעית דם revi'is dam in the
list of those things he reversed himself on, שהיא לימודו של רבי
עקיבא בידו, she-hi limuda she-Rabbi Akiva beyado, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva come,
you know, kept his teaching in his hand, meaning he held on
to his position. ועוד המקרא מסייעו, ve-od hamikra mesaye'o, and he's got
a good פסוק pasuk. for this one: ועל כל נפשות מת לא
יבא. ve-al kol nafshot met lo yavo. נפשות nafshot in the plural,
remember that was the דרשה drasha even coming from two separate and
you know, כי הדם הוא הנפש, ki hadam hu hanafesh, right, you
know, actually it's coming up this week in פרשת נח, parshas Noach,
what does it say? כי נפש כל בשר דמו בנפשו הוא, ki
nefesh kol basar damo benafsho hu, no, that's another one, that's not
נח.
Noach.
זה
וזה
דם הנפש?
ze v'ze
dam hanefesh? כי נפש כל בשר דמו
הוא.
ki nefesh kol basar damo hu.
Does it have דם dam and נפש nefesh in
נח?
Noach? אך בשר בנפשו דמו לא תאכלו. ach basar benafsho damo lo
socheilu. That's, אך בשר בנפשו דמו לא תאכלו, ach basar benafsho damo
lo socheilu, I think that's the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, so נפש nefesh
and דם dam their linking goes way throughout the תורה. Torah. Okay,
so נפשות מת nafshot met he understands has to do with דם
dam and it's in the plural. So he's got a פסוק. pasuk
That one he kept. That one he did not reverse himself on.
Which by the way might be why it said רביעית דם revi'is
dam and not חצי לוג דם. chatzi log dam. Because even though
we're talking about נזיר מגלח nazir migale'ach and the גמרא Gemara repeated
and we're talking about and it mentioned חצי קב עצמות. chatzi kav
atzamot. But because his לימוד limud from the פסוק pasuk starts from
a פסוק pasuk about נפשות מת nafshot met and starts with an
idea of רביעית דם revi'is dam for טומאת אוהל tumas ohel even
if maybe he does wind up doubling his שיעור shiur for נזיר
nazir which we don't know, does he double his שיעור shiur for
נזיר nazir or not? But anyway but his primary that's the one
he starts with a דרשה drasha from a, everything else is just
arbitrary. Here he starts from a דרשה drasha which starts with the
idea of רביעית דם, revi'is dam, which is why it was mentioned.
And that one he didn't reverse himself on. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi
Shimon Omer and remember the logic of רביעית דם, revi'is dam, what
I mentioned is, and the logic is as it says that a
that the רביעית דם revi'is dam is the is the amount of
blood that an infant like is born with. That's the minimum amount
that הנפש תלויה בו, hanefesh tluyah bo, that life is dependent on
when a child is just born. Okay, so that could be since
he's getting it from a פסוק pasuk and the logic, I'm sorry,
he's getting it from the פסוק Pasuk and the logic is
about רביעית, revi'it, might be why it mentioned רביעית revi'it there rather
than חצי לוג. chatzi log. Anyway, that's why we mentioned yes there
are seven. And and backbone are distinct, but we mentioned six because
he did not reverse himself by the רביעית revi'it of the blood.
Okay, ולא יפה. ve'lo yafeh. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, עד
ימיו היה מטמא. ad yamav haya metame. His entire his entire life,
Rabbi Akiva held onto his position about the blood that from two
separate bodies that causes טומאה. אם משמת חזר בו איני יודע. im
mishemet hazar bo ani lo yodea. If after he died he reversed
himself, I don't know. So you know, we're talking about living and
dying, so whatever.
So it's hard for a baby to ask him after he died.
So we all have a good laugh about that, but now we're
going to see the next line in the גמרא. Gemara תנא, Tana,
we taught a ברייתא, braita, הושחרו שיניו מפני תעניותיו. hushcharu shinav mipnei
taniyotav. He so regretted saying this disrespectful statement because Rabbi Akiva was
his רבי rebbe and making this like funny joke at Rabbi Akiva's
expense that he sat in so many fast days that his teeth
became black because to do תשובה teshuva for that.
So there you go, we all had the same laugh, so now
alright. Okay, תא שמע, tashma, come and hear. Even the גמרא Gemara
repeated it also, yes, yes.
So how much is
the I just looked, there's about one cup of blood in a
typical newborn baby.
Okay, and how much is a רביעית? revi'it? A רביעית revi'it is
about is the same שיעור shiur. that we use for what do
you call it? For קידוש. Kiddush. It's like three and a half
ounces.
Four
ounces,
yeah.
How much is a cup? How many ounces is a cup? Eight
ounces. Eight ounces. Aha. Well, so what's that, the average?
What's the what's why
what would be for a particularly small baby? What?
Alright. Alright, moving on. So it says like this. So
okay,
תנא, Tana, הוש... hush... oh, we just did that. תא שמע. ta
shma. Okay, so we're still not done yet with the skull and
the spinal cord. But also we taught a ברייתא, braita, בית שמאי
אומרים, Beit Shammai omrim, רוב עצמות מן העצמים rov atzamot min ha'atzamim
או משנים ומשלושה. o mishnayim u'mishlosha. When you measure this רובע rova
of a קב kav of bones, okay, how much we've discussed this
before, it has to come from a start from a pile of
bones that represent the whole body. So how many bones, like which
bones is it coming from? Okay, and basically you have this this
box you have filled with bones has like from each of the
you know, from each of the bones that are that combined represent
the body. So which bones are we talking about? So בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says it can come from like two or three. Okay,
it doesn't have to come from any specific amount or quantity of
bones, even from two or three bones, if you get that much
you know that it's all about the quantity seems to be what
they're saying. Okay, and בית הלל אומרים, Beit Hillel omrim, רובע מן
הגווייה. rova min hageviya. No, no, no. It has to come from
actually like the you know the the body itself, representing the body.
מרוב בניינו או מרוב מניינו. mi'rov binyano o mi'rov minyano. From either
the number, the majority of the number of bones, the גמרא Gemara
assumes that there are רמ"ח, rmach, ever hear that phrase? רמ"ח איברים?
rmach evarim? Right, which is assumes that that רמ"ח rmach bones, so
if there's a hundred no, actually no no no no. That's רמ"ח
איברים, rmach evarim, excuse me. So
it's what? It's שס"ה. shasa. Right, שס"ה.
shasa. Tendons are different, right?
No no no, I think Rabbi Dov is right. I think the
hold on, I think תוספות Tosafot quotes it here. Yeah. 365,
שס"ה. shasa. Yeah, hold on.
Veeder, hider,
sinew?
I remember limbs and ligaments.
Hold
on. Yeah. No. No no no no, I was right. This תוספות
Tosafot תא שמע, Shema he says the following. In the middle, like
right in the middle there, he says פירוש מעיקר הגווייה מרוב בניין
או מרוב מנין perush mi'ikar hageviya mi'rov binyan o mi'rov minyan שרמ"ח
איברים יש באדם she'rmach evarim yesh ba'adam כדתניא בריש מסכת אהלות ke'detanya
bereish masechet ohalot וקכ"ה הם רוב מנין. ve'kuf kaf hey hem rov
minyan. Okay, so 248, half of that is 124, so the רוב
rov is 125. All right, so somehow the assumption is that an
אבר evar each אבר evar has one bone. I don't know how
we have 200 248 איברים evarim anyway. I mean bones might make
sense. Right, we don't have 248 limbs. So anyway, so presumably makes
more sense to read אבר ever there as a bone anyway. All
right, so בית הלל Beit Hillel says it has to come from
the majority of the numbers or from the bones that make up
the majority of the structure. אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, יכול
אני לעשות דברי בית שמאי ודברי בית הלל כאחד. yachol ani la'asot
divrei Beit Shammai ve'divrei Beit Hillel ke'echad. Rabbi Yehoshua said, I could
say they're really not debating. How are they not debating? One says
two or three bones and the other says רוב בניין rov binyan
or רוב מניין. rov minyan. שבית שמאי אומרים משנים ומשלושה she'Beit Shammai
omrim mishnayim u'mishlosha או משתי שוקיים וירך אחד o mishtei shokaim ve'yerech
echad או משתי ירכיים ושוק אחד. o mishtei yerechayim ve'shok echad. Either
from
two calves and one thigh or from two thighs and one calf.
So that's two or three, I mean it's really three. Okay, but
that's רוב בניינה. rov binyana. That's interesting, I would have said רוב
בניין rov binyan you know, I mean even if most at like
are most of people's heights in their legs? Like more of the
height from the waist down than the waist up or it depends
on the person?
You mean the variability?
I just mean like if
you the...
Actually no wait I know this from anatomy and drawing, it's slightly,
the pelvis sits slightly higher than the halfway point. Slightly.
Slightly higher. But you see but the funny thing is if you
do the thigh and the and the calf, you do the thigh
and that's below the pelvis, right? So it's not, it doesn't include
the hip bone.
Right, so it hooks in, so where it hooks
in
is almost exactly at the middle.
Where it hooks in? Where it hooks into the hip bone is
that is that at the middle? Okay, so that's interesting, so okay,
so this is assuming that between the thigh and the calf that
that's at least the majority of your that's the majority of your
height. Okay, so and then it is that's number one assumption, right?
And then number two, not just it's half your height, it's the
majority of your height, and then it assumes that you only need
the majority of that. So if you have two calves, you know,
two thighs and a calf or two calves and a thigh, right?
And if you think about it, if the person was alive, two
thighs and a calf they could they could that could work. Right?
Two
calves and a thigh doesn't work. The calf doesn't have anything to
connect to the body with. But somehow the majority of the structure
that itself is the majority of the height of the person, that's
considered to be רוב בניינה. rov binyana. Okay, so that's where we're
getting that from. Did you want to say something?
No, it's okay, I don't know if it's actually accurate, I just
know that that was proportional anatomy.
Right, I got it. Okay, but the point is it's actually, I
mean, yeah, it would seem though once you're going from right not
the actual waist itself but from the calf, it's not so clear
that the calf and the thigh, I mean from the thigh, the
thigh and the calf together it's not so clear make up rov
of the height. And even with that we're just saying rov of
that, of those four bones, three of those four bones. Yes, Charlie.
A typical adult human has exactly 206 bones. Some start off with
more bones, and
at birth it's 270.
And at birth it's 270. So it's somewhere between the two. And
at some point in your life you probably have 248.
All
right. Okay.
Now okay.
So anyway when Beit Shammai says two or three, he really meant
the thighs and the calf and that's what he meant by two
or three and he really was his way of saying רוב בניין.
rov binyan. Okay? משני שוקים וירך אחד או
משני ירכיים ושוק אחד. הוא רוב גובהו של
אדם mishnei shokayim veyarech echad o mishnei yerechayim veshok echad. hovei rov
govho shel adam מגובהו או בגודלו. migovho o begodlo. This since that
is most of a person's height. Okay. ובית הלל אומרים מן הגוויה
u-veit hillel omrim min hagviya from the from like the body itself,
like the, ומי רוב בניין או רוב מניין, u-mi rov binyan o
rov minyan, הוא וישנן במפרקי ידיים ורגליים hovei ve-yeshnan be-mifarkei yadayim ve-raglayim
because basically you can get a lot of, now it's funny, Beit
Hillel says רוב בניין rov binyan but he's sort of trying to
have Beit Shammai saying one thing, רוב בניין, rov binyan, and Beit
Hillel saying the other thing, רוב מניין, rov minyan, and that you
can get רוב מניין rov minyan from the הגוויה hagviya normally also
up from I think more suggests the torso, and he's saying that
there you can actually get רוב מניין rov minyan because there's so
many bones in the hand, well not the torso but the feet.
Anyway, in the hands and the feet you got a lot of
small little bones, so you can get רוב מניין rov minyan without
getting רוב בניין rov binyan if you get all the small bones
in the hands and the feet. All right. So basically he's basically
saying I don't want to say that Beit Shammai really just means
any two or three bones, I'm going to say that Beit Shammai
also fundamentally means רוב בניין rov binyan and he's talking about a
particular two or three bones. All right. So now the Gemara continues.
Okay. שמאי אומר אפילו עצם מן השדרה או מן הגולגולת. shammai omer
afilu etzem min hashidra o min hagulgoles. Okay. Now we finally get
to the reason we quoted all of this, was not for the
רוב מניין rov minyan and רוב בניין, rov binyan, but that's important
okay for the idea of רובע rova but we're not focusing right
now on רובע rova or חצי קב, chatzi kav, we're focusing on
שדרה וגולגולת. shidra ve-gulgoles. So the reason we quoted it is for
the following line, that Shammai says even a small piece of bone
from,
where are we, אפילו עצם, afilu etzem, even one bone from the
backbone or from the skull, not a small piece, maybe a full
bone, but any one bone from the backbone or the skull is
enough.
Wait, so Shammai, Beit Shammai disagrees with Shammai?
No, we weren't talking about the skull and the backbone before, we
were talking about just other bones. There's two categories, right, of bones.
There's רובע חצי קב rova chatzi kav okay from רוב מניין רוב
בניין, rov minyan rov binyan, that was one debate that Beit Shammai
said two out of from two or three and Beit Hillel said
רוב מניין רוב בניין rov minyan rov binyan and Rabbi Yehoshua won
to say they're saying the same thing. And then there's the other
category of bones which is skull and backbone. Okay, so in the
skull and backbone issue, we have another debate, that Shammai says one
bone out of the skull and backbone.
And they look like the jaw because otherwise it's all the head?
Is the skull two hemispheres or is it fused? There's several plates
that are fused.
There's several plates.
Okay. Anyway, so they say one bone out of either one or
the other. So the implication would be that what would be the
opposing position? You would need the entire skull or the entire backbone,
but not that you would need the skull and the backbone combined.
Right, Shammai says one from the skull or one from the backbone
is enough. So presumably that suggests that according to Hillel and the
other opinion you need the whole skull and the whole or or
the whole backbone. But Shammai... שמאי שמאי שמאי דמחמיר, Shammai Shammai Shammai
d'machmir, שמאי Shammai is very strict. And maybe he says, maybe בית
הלל Beis Hillel or הלל Hillel or whoever requires the whole bone
plus the whole skull plus the whole backbone, and שמאי Shammai is
very, very strict. One or the other and even one bone from
one of the other. So you can't figure out what the other
position is from שמאי. Shammai. So the גמרא Gemara. says, ולישמעי דטעמא
דבית שמאי דמחמיר, U'lishmeih d'ta'ama d'Beis Shammai d'machmir, הני רבנן עד דאיכא
שדרה וגולגולת. Hanei Rabbanan ad d'ika shidra v'gulgoles. So fine, let's infer
the other way. שמאי Shammai goes to one extreme, let's assume the
רבנן Rabbanan go to the other extreme and require
the whole backbone and the whole skull? No, not necessarily. אי הכי
ליפלגו רבנן עליה דשמאי אלא בעצם אחד, Ei hachi liflgu Rabbanan alei
d'Shammai ela b'etzem echad, דאתי מן השדרה ומן הגולגולת. d'asi min hashidra
u'min hagulgoles. No, they're only debating the question of one bone. שמאי
Shammai says that's enough, but they would say you need the whole
thing. אבל היכא דאיתא בעיניה, Aval heicha d'isa b'einei, if you have
the whole skull or the whole backbone, אפילו חד מינייהו, afilu chad
mineihu, even one of them. Which is basically a way of saying
you don't know what the opposing position is. Okay, is the opposing
position you need the whole skull plus the whole backbone or the
whole skull or the whole backbone?
You can't posit the other position if you posit the first.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, so basically we don't know in the end of
this, we don't know the answer, although all of the evidence pretty
strongly suggests one or the other. Let me just look up how
the רמב"ם Rambam paskens about this.
Oh,
are we going to get an answer? No, that's the end of
that, I mean we're going to continue another discussion, but that is
the end of that, no, not the end of the דף. daf
That was the end of those that discussion. Okay.
It's pretty clear that all the evidence is lining up to be
one or the other. I mean, that you don't need both.
Both is definitely not the conclusion.
It's only both since all the evidence is lining up that it's
one or the
other. Let's look at the רמב"ם. Rambam. טומאת
מת Tumas Meis פרק
ח׳. Perek Ches. Okay.
כל בנין של אדם הוא
שתי השוקיים
וירכיים
והצלעות
והשדרה,
Kol binyan shel adam
hu shtei hashokayim v'yerechayim
v'hatzla'os
v'hashidra,
that's your entire בניין, binyan, are your calves and your thighs and
your ribs and your backbone. ורוב בניינו הרי הוא כמת שלם. V'rov
binyano harei hu k'meis shaleim. That's רוב בניין. rov binyan.
Hold on, let me see the שדרה shidra and the גולגולת. gulgoles.
Okay. ואלו הן העצמות שמטמאין במת: השדרה והגולגולת, רוב
בניינו ורוב מניינו. V'eileh ha'atzamos shemetamin b'meis: hashidra v'hagulgoles, rov binyano v'rov
minyano. השדרה כיצד? Hashidra keitzad? שדרה ששלמה הרי היא כמת
שלם, Shidra sheshleimah harei hi k'meis shaleim, da da da. גולגולת כיצד?
Gulgoles keitzad? גולגולת ששלמה הרי היא כמת שלם.
Gulgoles sheshleimah harei hi k'meis shaleim. So the
רמב"ם Rambam is one or the other, which is clearly where all
the evidence was going. Okay, so now let's see where the גמרא
Gemara says. Next question in the גמרא. Gemara בעי רמי בר חמא,
Ba'ei Rami Bar Chama, רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama asked the
following question. רוב עצמות מן השדרה והגולגולת מאי? Rov atzamos min hashidra
v'hagulgoles mai? Let's say you do not have a whole שדרה shidra
and a whole גולגולת, gulgoles, which we said basically you needed both
to be whole or maybe you even needed both combined or one
or the other, but what you do have is you have the
quantity that we've been talking about, a רביעית revi'is or חצי קב
chatzi kav depending on whether you're talking about a נזיר Nazir or
in general. You have the quantity. Now, this quantity we said was
significant when it came from bones that themselves represented the מת, meis,
right? It came from רוב מניין rov minyan or רוב בניין. rov
binyan. So the גמרא Gemara is asking a very reasonable question. Let's
say you get this quantity that comes from the שדרה shidra or
the גולגולת. gulgoles. Since those themselves also represent the מת, meis, right,
maybe a quantity that's not the entire שדרה shidra and גולגולת gulgoles
but that comes from that should also be enough. Is that clear,
right? Because you've got רוב מניין rov minyan and רוב בניין, rov
binyan, okay, and not only do those cause it but even if
it's a רביעית revi'is coming from it. And until now we've said
that you've got also have this idea of שדרה shidra and גולגולת.
gulgoles.
So גולגולת, gulgoles, we said the entire thing. Let's say you don't
have the entire thing, but let's say you have a quantity, okay,
that's enough that comes from something that represents the whole מת, meis,
maybe that
should
be enough as well.
Yes, talking about טומאת אוהל.
tumas ohel. טומאת אוהל. Tumas ohel. Even טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, right.
Bones, even a small piece of bone is טמא through touch. So
all this is what's necessary for טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. Okay, so
yeah, so it says like this.
אמר רבא, תא
שמע. Amar Rava ta shema, Okay, where were we? בעי רמי בר
חמא, Ba'ei Rami Bar Chama, excuse me, רוב עצמות מן השדרה והגולגולת
מאי? rov atzamos min hashidra v'hagulgoles mai? כי תני חצי קב עצמות
Ki tanyi chatzi kav atzamos or חצי chatzi or רובע, rova, it's
not that's not relevant here, just depends on נזיר Nazir or something
else. היכא דאיכא משאר איבריו, Heicha d'ika mishar evarav, when it's coming
from the other bones, meaning רוב מניין rov minyan or רוב בניין
rov binyan as we discussed before, אבל מן השדרה והגולגולת... aval min
hashidra v'hagulgoles... Oh no no, I’m sorry, I misread it. No, it
is about the difference between חצי chatzi and רובע. rova. So I
framed the question about whether any שיעור Shiur? is meaningful, or do
you always need the entire amount. Okay, that’s why I framed the
question. But really רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama is asking a
second-level question. He’s assuming that a שיעור shiur. is significant from a
שדרה וגולגולת, shidra ve-galgoret, even if it’s not whole. And his only
question is whether you need the חצי קב chatzi kav or the
רובע קב. rova kav. Okay. Maybe even for a נזיר, Nazir, maybe
even a רובע קב rova kav would be enough. So he’s number
one taking it for granted that a חצי קב chatzi kav is
going to be an issue even if it’s not whole. And then
saying, but since the skull and the backbone are so significant as
representing the מת, meit, maybe even half the שיעור should be enough
for נזיר מגלח Nazir megaleach to have the same weight as a
חצי קב. chatzi kav. Let’s take a look. Let’s read that again.
בעי רמי בר חמא, Ba’ei Rami bar Chama, רובע עצמות משדרה וגולגולת
מאי? rova atzamot mishidra ve-galgoret mai? כי תניא חצי קב, Ki tanya
chatzi kav, when is there a requirement for a half קב kav
עצמות atzamot normally? היכא דאיכא משאר איברים, Heicha de-ika mish’ar evarav, when
it’s from the other bones, just רובע מניין rova minyan or רובע
בניין, rova binyan, but bones that in themselves don’t carry a lot
of weight and significance. אבל משדרה וגולגולת, Aval mishidra ve-galgoret, if it’s
coming
from the backbone or the skull דחמירי de-chamiri that they say even
a single one of those
is טומאת אוהל, tumat ohel, so those each one of them carries
a lot of weight, אפילו רובע עצמות, afilu rova atzamot, even a
רובע rova should be enough, even for a נזיר. Nazir. או דילמא
לא שנא, O dilma lo shana, maybe it doesn’t matter. So assuming
that quantity is significant by this, he says even a smaller quantity
should carry equal weight to a, you know, to for a נזיר
Nazir for חצי קב. chatzi kav. אמר רבא Amar Rava, תא שמע,
Shema come and hear. השדרה והגולגולת, Hashidra ve-hagalgoret, the
משנה Mishnah lists שדרה וגולגולת. shidra ve-galgoret. ואי סלקא דעתך רובע עצמות
דאתי משדרה וגולגולת חמיר, Ve-i salka da’atach rova atzamot de-ati mishidra ve-galgoret
chamir, if there was also a measure in our case of נזיר,
Nazir, because our משנה Mishnah is about נזיר, Nazir, right? Our משנה
Mishnah said חצי קב chatzi kav by the other bones. So if
there was for example where a רובע עצמות rova atzamot קב kav
would be significant by these bones, ליתני או רובע עצמות הבא מן
השדרה, litni o rova atzamot ha-ba min ha-shidra, list it in the
משנה. Mishnah. Right? The משנה Mishnah said a whole שדרה, shidra, a
whole גולגולת, galgoret, then it said חצי קב עצמות. chatzi kav atzamot.
So he’s sort of saying, I will take for granted that the
חצי קב עצמות chatzi kav atzamot again, we’re going to take for
granted, applies not only to רוב מניין rov minyan and רוב בניין
rov binyan but also applies to שדרה וגולגולת. shidra ve-galgoret. That’s fine.
We’ll take that for granted. That applies to any collection of bones
that is significant, whether it’s רוב מניין, rov minyan, whether it’s רוב
בניין, rov binyan, whether it’s the שדרה shidra or the גולגולת. galgoret.
But it sounds like that’s the only quantity that matters. It sounds
like for a נזיר Nazir there’s no רביעית. revi'it. If there was
a רביעית revi'it that would apply by שדרה וגולגולת, shidra ve-galgoret, it
should have mentioned that, not just mentioned the חצי קב. chatzi kav.
So that’s a very good point. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
רבא, Ve-ha Rava, one minute, והא רבא הוא דאמר, ve-ha Rava hu
de-amar, but didn’t רבא Rava say in another context לא נצרכה אלא
לשדרה וגולגולת שאין בהם רובע עצמות, lo nitzrecha ela le-shidra ve-galgoret she-ein
bahem rova atzamot, that it was needed for a case of a
שדרה וגולגולת shidra ve-galgoret that don’t have a רובע עצמות? rova atzamot?
Now, what is this other context that רבא Rava said? So it
seems to be going back to, but there's a whole complication here
whether it really refers to that because it wasn't what we said
before. But it seems to be going back to, remember the first
question the גמרא Gemara’s asked, which is why does it have to
say מת meit if it’s saying a כזית מן המת? kezayit min
ha-meit? Why does it have to say the whole corpse, right? So
one of the answers was that we’re talking about a miscarriage and
the baby was so small and it didn’t have, it didn’t have
like you know, it didn’t have some of the other criteria. So
the גמרא Gemara here seems to be framing it although that wasn’t
what it said earlier, right? If you take a look back earlier
on נ, nun, רבא Rava said אלא לרוב בניינו ולרוב מניינו
שאין בהם רובע עצמות, ela le-rov binyano u-le-rov minyano she-ein bahem rova
atzamot, that it was a case that the baby was so small
that you had all of the majority of the bones and the
majority of the structure and it still would not have a רובע
עצמות. rova atzamot. Okay, that’s what he said before. The גמרא's Gemara
version of this is שדרה וגולגולת שאין בהם רובע עצמות. shidra ve-galgoret
she-ein bahem rova atzamot. You have the skull or the backbone and
it did not have that amount, that quantity. And nevertheless, if you
have the skull or the backbone, even if it doesn’t have a
certain quantity, you’re still going to, it’s still going to be טמא.
Okay. So the upshot of that is, you have, you know, נעבעך,
nebech, you have a, you have a small fetus that has and
the skull and the backbone combined are not this רובע הקב, rova
ha-kav, but because it’s a whole skull or a whole backbone, that
causes טומאה. If you have the whole thing, you don’t need the
quantitative amount. Okay. So now what we would be saying is, and
this gets back to the point we said before, שדרה או גולגולת
shidra o galgoret by themselves causes טומאה or a quantity that comes
from the שדרה וגולגולת shidra ve-galgoret causes טומאה. If you’ve got enough
quantity, you don’t need the whole thing. And if you’ve got the
whole thing, you don’t need enough quantity. What’s significant for us though
is that the version here of what רבא said was שאין בהם
רובע עצמות. she-ein bahem rova atzamot. Not שאין בהם חצי קב עצמות,
she-ein bahem chatzi kav atzamot, but שאין בהם
רובע עצמות. she-ein bahem rova atzamot. So that seems to be assuming
that when it is a quantity that comes from the שדרה וגולגולת
shidra ve-galgoret You don't need a חצי קב. chatzi kav. It seems
to be assuming you only need a quarter of a kav, which
is exactly רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama question. So again, we're
assuming that the normal חצי קב chatzi kav comes from a collection
of bones that is significant, we've either או רובינן או שדרה וגולגולת
o rovinan o shidrah ve-gulgollet and רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama
saying maybe שדרה וגולגולת shidrah ve-gulgollet since they're so weighty, even a
רביעית הקב. revi'is hakav. Okay, and the point is he didn't say
it in the משנה, Mishna, the משנה Mishna only said חצי. chatzi.
Ah, but רבא himself has pointed out it didn't say it in
the משנה, Mishna, himself implied by this statement that he made that
a רביעית הקב revi'is hakav would be enough. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. So בתר דשמיע מרבי עקיבא. batar deshami mi-Rabbi
Akiva. So that was, you know what, after he heard it, now
who's this רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Nobody exactly knows what this רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is. תוספות Tosafot is set, goes to a long
תוספות Tosafot. trying to figure out what exactly this means. But anyway,
it means that after he heard it, basically it tries to say
after he heard, you know, the position of רמי בר חמא, Rami
bar Chama, I mean it's not רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, there's no
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but who was it? It was רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama asked him this question. Anyway, after he heard
רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama suggestion that maybe a רביעית הקב
revi'is hakav would be enough, so then he reversed himself. Initially he
took the position you need a חצי קב, chatzi kav, this statement
of a רביעית הקב revi'is hakav came after he sort of like
reconsidered, you know,
after he...
Okay, but it doesn't answer the question. But it might be, okay,
but nevertheless, but we can't prove it. I mean, he himself might
in the end have been thinking that a רביעית הקב revi'is hakav
would be would be enough, but we still haven't proved it. The
משנה Mishna says חצי קב. chatzi kav. Okay, so we still don't
know exactly what the story is and we'll continue looking at this
tomorrow.
Is it continuing רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
Yeah, a long תוספות. Tosafos He tries, yeah.
Again. Here, take a look. That's ironic. We just mentioned a רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that reversed. Yeah, I don't know what to say
about that.
Rabbi, we are we are no longer one day ahead.
What? We're two days ahead?
We are now two days ahead.
I know. So what are we going to do about it? Take
a vacation?
I know.
You
can't take a vacation.
can't take a vacation from דף היומי, Daf Yomi, right? You mentioned
that for some reason some people want to say חצבא chatzba of
רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva.
Actually, it could be for anybody to say חצבא. chatzba.
Well, חצבא chatzba of בית ספק? Beis Safek? Argue all you want,
and there's... you never convince anyone. You could argue all you want.
That's a good point.
I don't know if that...
I guess we're trying to convince a different audience.
Like we're going to speak our
opinion,
but we're going to try to convince everybody else besides... Okay, can
I follow you?
They used to have בית ספק Beis Safek to...
oh well
that has to do with the טומאת
נוכרי.
tum'at
nochri. טומאת נוכרי tum'at nochri and are they מטמא באוהל? metameh be-ohel?
A lot of כוהנים Kohanim are מחמיר. machmir. It seems like the
בית ספק Beis Safek says the נוכרי nochri is not מטמא באוהל,
metameh be-ohel,
but there are definitely כוהנים Kohanim that would be
מטמא באוהל, metameh be-ohel, right?
Yeah. But I have blood, so there's definitely כוהנים Kohanim that are
מחמיר machmir for it. Like I have...
just enjoy it.
You'll see I'm there,
you'll see take a look.
Okay,
and, you know, it basically just, I mean, I have to now
match what I had in my imagination. Well, this here's the point,
this I think is
not based on archaeological evidence, it's based on just their best reconstruction
of what... Now there actually is a book called כלי חרס בתקופת
התלמוד Klei Heres bitkufat haTalmud and כלי זכוכית בתקופת התלמוד Klei Zechuchit
bitkufat haTalmud which actually draws, you know, starts with all the archaeological
evidence and works back. So if you really want to be academic
about it I could give you that. But this will help you
more just getting through the
משניות mishnayos
and the סוגיא.
sugya. Here. Yeah, let me see if I've got the other book
around here. Yeah, I mean if you want to you can borrow
it. My כלי חרס Klei Heres one looks like it was dug
up in an archaeological find. I got it used or whatever. But
this is this is actually based on, you know, the actual archaeological
evidence, so it's like חצבא, chatzba, got a whole chapter on
חצבא, chatzba, and it has pictures.
No, I mean, and this is the כלי זכוכית Klei Zechuchit which
is by the same guy which is actually in a readable format.
Okay, looks like it has fewer pictures though. That's helpful.
Okay, this helps
me.
All right, very good. Oh here are some pictures. Yeah.
Okay,
I need...
okay, I think this should do.
Even if they're not exactly accurate, it gives you an idea. Let
me just remember exactly where that line is
and okay,
I gotta
go.
Let's go רבות.
rabos. Okay, thank you Rabbi. Yeah.
Hey, I'll
see
you one day
when I have my phone pictures. Rabbi, 14
זוז? zuz?
No, go ahead, go ahead.
Yeah,
I
had
14 זוז zuz
for something else that you... I was wondering if you brought that.
You can't use that because I don't have the... I'll give it
to somebody else, we don't have a change machine here. Take it
back. Give it to someone else. Yeah, take it back. Yeah, I
have no need for it. Give it back to someone else, yeah.
I have no need for it because I don't have, I don't
have, give it to somebody else. All right, fine. Go ahead, I'm
going to look into this later. Okay, everybody, I'm locking up. This
is why it's so amazing and it's very unusual for you to
see. Everybody out.
The exhibits of sculptures from this early.
The
things that I have, I've
had to
add to the
museum to
say, it's the first that
I...
yeah. The earliest
sculpture they have is from 1903. Well, yeah,
well, yeah, he was doing these pieces, yeah,
1914, 15. All right, I'll see you at
about 3:30 or so. Yeah. I'll be דאווענען
davening at that time. Go ahead. No, no,
you can stay. Wait, 3:30? Yeah. That's when
I'll be... I'll be finishing up, up in
the museum. The גמרא Gemara in מסכת סוכה Maseches Sukkah דף
כח עמוד א daf chaf ches amud aleph tells us about the
גדלות gadlus of יונתן בן עוזיאל Yonasan ben Uziel that when he
would sit and learn תורה Torah any bird that
flew over him would be immediately נשרף nisraf from
the קדושה kedusha of his לימוד. limud. Now, what about
checking your clothes on שבת? Shabbos? We see in
the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch in סימן ש"ב סעיף ב'
Siman Shin Beis Saif Beis that it is מותר
Mutar to check your clothes. Why is it
different? So, the משנה ברורה Mishna Brurah explains that by
a שוחט, Shochet, he is very careful and he
is in a rush to do the שחיטה,
Shechita, so we are worried he will fix
it. But by clothes, you are not in
such a rush. There is also the question
of בורר. Borer. If you are looking for dirt,
are you doing בורר? Borer? The answer is that
because looking is not a physical מעשה, Maaseh, it
is not considered בורר. Borer. Therefore, it is מותר
Mutar to check your clothes to see if
they are clean on שבת. Shabbos. Now, why do
we do this? Why is it important to
have a beautiful מצוה? mitzvah? Because it shows our
love for השם. Hashem. It shows that we're not just doing the
מצוה mitzvah because we have to, but because we want to. We
want to do it in the best way possible. And this is
also true when it comes to תפילה. Tefillah. We should try to
דאוון daven in a way that is beautiful. Meaning, we should have
כוונה. kavanah. And we should try to understand the words that we're
saying. So, the next time you're doing a מצוה, mitzvah, think about
how you can make it more beautiful. Think about how you can
fulfill the concept of הידור מצוה. Hiddur Mitzvah. And it's not just
about the physical object; it's also about the way we do it.
So if we're doing a מצוה mitzvah with a smile and with
a good attitude, that's also a form of הידור מצוה. Hiddur Mitzvah.
Because we're making the מצוה mitzvah more pleasant for ourselves and for
others. And that's a very important thing to remember. So, I hope
this was helpful and I hope you have a great day. The
13th of אדר Adar is תענית אסתר. Ta'anit Esther. Now, we know
that actually אסתר Esther fasted on the 13th, 14th, and 15th of
ניסן. Nisan. That was when המן Haman made the גזירה. gezeirah. So
why do we fast on the 13th of אדר? Adar? The answer
is that it's a זכר zecher to the fast that the בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael made on the 13th of אדר Adar when they
fought their enemies. Whenever the יהודים Yehudim went to war, they would
fast and pray to הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. We see
this by משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu when he fought against עמלק. Amalek.
He was on the mountain and he fasted. So on the 13th
of אדר, Adar, they fasted and they fought. And we call it
תענית אסתר Ta'anit Esther because she was the one who showed the
power of fasting for the יהודים. Yehudim. The provided audio contains only
background noise and no discernible speech. No transcription is possible. The laws
of טומאה *Tumah* and טהרה tahara *Taharah* depend on the specific type
of טומאה *Tumah* a person has. The רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* in the
beginning of הלכות halachos ביאת המקדש *Hilchos Bi'as HaMikdash* clarifies these boundaries.
He explains that there are שלוש מחנות *shalosh machanos*, three distinct areas.
The מחנה שכינה Shechinah *Machaneh Shechinah* starts from the פתח העזרה *Pesach
HaAzarah* and goes inward. The מחנה לוייה *Machaneh Leviyah* is the area
from the פתח הר הבית *Pesach Har HaBayis* up to the wall
of the עזרה *Azarah*. And the מחנה ישראל *Machaneh Yisrael* spans from
the פתח ירושלים *Pesach Yerushalayim* until the הר הבית *Har HaBayis*. A
מצורע *Metzora* is treated with the most חומרא *chumra*, stringency. He is
sent out of all שלוש מחנות *shalosh machanos*, meaning he must remain
outside the walls of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. The משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* explains that this applies to both
a מצורע מוסגר *Metzora musgar* and a מצורע
מוחלט *Metzora muchlat*. Now, the זב *Zav*, the
זבה *Zavah*, the נדה *Niddah*, and the יולדת
*Yoledet* have a different status. They are only
excluded from two camps. While they can be
in מחנה ישראל *Machaneh Yisrael* and walk the
streets of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, they are forbidden from
entering מחנה לוייה *Machaneh Leviyah*, which is the
הר הבית *Har HaBayis*. Lastly, we have the
טמא מת *Tamei Meis*. Even though a מת
*meis* is the אבי אבות הטומאה *Avi Avos
HaTumah*, the source of all impurity, the restriction
is surprisingly lenient compared to the others. The
טמא מת *Tamei Meis* is only excluded from
מחנה שכינה *Machaneh Shechinah*. He is allowed to
be in מחנה לוייה *Machaneh Leviyah*, meaning he
can go onto the הר הבית *Har HaBayis*.
This distinction teaches us a major principle in
the laws of טומאה *Tumah*. The level of
הרחקה *herchaka* or distance one must keep from
the מקדש mikdash, *Mikdash* is not solely determined by
the intensity of the טומאה *tumah*. Even though
a מת *meis* is a higher level of
טומאה *tumah* than a זב *zav*, the זב
*zav* is more restricted. The מפרשים *meforshim* explain
that because the טומאה *tumah* of a זב
*zav* or a מצורע *metzora* is a טומאה
היוצאת מגופו *tumah hayotzeis migufo*, an impurity that
originates from within the person's own body, it
carries a certain חומרא *chumra* regarding where they
may go. This internal impurity requires a further
level of separation. These definitions of מחנה שכינה
*Machaneh Shechinah*, מחנה לוייה *Machaneh Leviyah*, and מחנה
ישראל *Machaneh Yisrael* are essential for understanding how
we maintain the קדושה Kedusha *kedusha* of the מקדש
*Mikdash* and ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. We see from here
that the מחנה שכינה *Machaneh Shechinah* is the
most holy. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in מסכת פסחים
Pesachim *Masechet Pesachim* discusses the source for these
laws. It says וישלחו מן המחנה *Viyishalchu min
hamachaneh*. Why does it say מחנה *machaneh* in
the singular if there are three? The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says it is to teach us
that each one is sent out from its
respective מחנה *machaneh*. The מצורע *Metzora* from all
three, the זב *Zav* from two, and the
טמא מת *Tamei Meis* from one. This is
based on the logic that the מצורע *Metzora*
has the most intense טומאה *tumah*. His טומאה
*tumah* can even be מטמא metameh *metamei* through ביאה
*bi'ah*, through entering a house. Therefore, he is
kept furthest away. But then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
asks about the זב *Zav* and the טמא
מת *Tamei Meis*. We would expect the טמא
מת *Tamei Meis* to be more restricted. But
the תורה Torah *Torah* says otherwise. And the reason,
as we said, is because the זב *Zav*
is a טומאה היוצאת מגופו *tumah hayotzeis migufo*.
This means the source of the impurity is
the person himself. With a טמא מת *Tamei
Meis*, he is merely a carrier of impurity
from an outside source. This distinction is crucial
in הלכות טומאה וטהרה *Hilchos Tumah viTaharah*. And
it is important to remember that these laws
of מחנות *machanos* apply even today in a
certain sense regarding our access to the מקום
המקדש *Mekom HaMikdash*. Even though we are all
טמאי מתים *tamei meisim* today, we would technically
be allowed in מחנה לוייה *Machaneh Leviyah* if
not for other factors. But someone who is
a זב *zav* would still be forbidden from
the הר הבית *Har HaBayis*. When we have
the Simcha שמחה Simcha of Sukkos סוכות, Sukkos, it is
called Zman Simchatenu זמן שמחתנו. Zman Simchatenu. And the reason
it's called Zman Simchatenu זמן שמחתנו Zman Simchatenu is because
it is a time of our joy. Now,
what's the difference between this Simcha שמחה Simcha? and
other types of Simcha שמחה? Simcha The Torah תורה
Torah. tells us that on Sukkos סוכות Sukkos we
have to be completely happy. We have to
be Ach Sameach אך שמח. Ach Sameach. What is Ach
Sameach אך שמח? Ach Sameach? It means only happy. There
should be nothing else in our hearts except
for the Simcha שמחה Simcha of the Mitzvah מצוה.
Mitzvah. And we see this also in the
Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. During the times of
the Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, there was something
called the Simchas Beis Hashoeva שמחת בית השואבה.
Simchas Beis Hashoeva. The Gemara גמרא Gemara tells us
that anyone who did not see the Simchas
Beis Hashoeva שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva never saw Simcha
שמחה Simcha in his life. And why is it
called the Simchas Beis Hashoeva שמחת בית השואבה?
Simchas Beis Hashoeva? The Gemara גמרא Gemara says because
it was a drawing of the Ruach Hakodesh
רוח הקודש. Ruach Hakodesh. From there they would draw the
Ruach Hakodesh רוח הקודש. Ruach Hakodesh. This was the highest
level of Simcha שמחה Simcha that a person could
achieve. Now we don't have the Beis Hamikdash
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash today, but we still have the
Mitzvah מצוה Mitzvah of Simcha שמחה Simcha on the Yom
Tov יום טוב Yom Tov of Sukkos סוכות. Sukkos. And the
way we fulfill this Mitzvah מצוה Mitzvah is by
being happy with what we have and by
being happy with the Torah תורה. Torah Because at
the end of Sukkos סוכות, Sukkos, we have the
Simcha שמחה Simcha of Shemini Atzeret שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret and
Simchat Torah שמחת תורה. Simchat Torah. And on Simchat Torah
שמחת תורה, Simchat Torah, we finish the Torah תורה Torah and
we start it again. This shows that our
Simcha שמחה Simcha is eternal. It never ends. Just
like the Torah תורה Torah never ends, our Simcha
שמחה Simcha with the Torah תורה Torah. never ends. The
Rambam רמבם Rambam tells us in Hilchos Lulav הלכות
לולב Hilchos Lulav that the Simcha שמחה Simcha, that a person
has in doing a Mitzvah מצוה Mitzvah is a
great Avodah עבודה. Avodah. It's a way of serving
Hashem השם. Hashem. And if a person doesn't have
this Simcha שמחה, Simcha then he is missing something
very important in his service of Hashem השם.
Hashem. As the Pasuk פסוק pasuk, says, Tachat Asher
Lo Avadata Et Hashem Elokecha BeSimcha UveTuv Levav
תחת אשר לא עבדת את השם אלקיך בשמחה
ובטוב לבב. Tachat Asher Lo Avadata Et Hashem Elokecha BeSimcha UveTuv Levav.
Because you did not serve Hashem השם Hashem your
G-d with joy and with a good heart.
This shows us how crucial the Simcha שמחה
Simcha. is. So on Sukkos סוכות, Sukkos, we try
to reach that level. We sit in the
Sukkah סוכה, Sukkah, which is the Tzila DeHeimanuta צלא
דהימנותא. Tzila DeHeimanuta. The shadow of faith. When we sit
in the Sukkah סוכה, Sukkah, we are surrounding ourselves
with the Kedusha קדושה Kedusha of the Mitzvah מצוה.
Mitzvah. And this Kedusha קדושה kedusha brings us to
a state of true Simcha שמחה. Simcha A Simcha
שמחה Simcha. that is not dependent on anything physical.
It's a spiritual Simcha שמחה. Simcha And that is
why it is called Zman Simchatenu זמן שמחתנו.
Zman Simchatenu. It's the time of our joy,
specifically our joy in our connection to Hashem
השם Hashem and the Torah תורה. Torah May we all
be Zocheh זוכה Zocheh to feel this Simcha שמחה
this year and every year. Amen אמן. Amen. So
we can learn out from this פסוק, pasuk who
is he מטמא metameh for? He's מטמא metameh for his
wife who is כשרה. ksheira. So we learn out
from here that a כהן kohen can be מטמא
for his wife. And it says by his
wife שאר she'er and שאר she'er means wife. How do
we know that? Because we see in the beginning of פרשת אחרי
מות, Parshas Acharei Mos, the פסוק pasuk says אל כל שאר בשרו
לא תקרבו לגלות ערווה al kol she'er besaro lo tikrevu legalot ervah
and that means husband and wife. Another point about husband and wife,
the word for wife is אשה isha and the word for husband
is איש. ish. If you look at the letters they both have
the letters א alef and ש shin and אש esh means fire.
So if the husband and wife fight then there's fire between them.
But the husband has the letter י yud and the wife has
the letter ה hei and if they have שלום בית shalom bayis
between them they have ה' Hashem between them because י yud and
ה hei is one of the names of ה'. Hashem. So this
was about husband and wife. Hello and welcome to the daily פרשה
parsha שיעור. Today we're going to talk about פרשת ויחי. Parshas Vayechi.
In the beginning of the פרשה, parsha, we see that יעקב אבינו
Yaakov Avinu lived in מצרים Mitzrayim for seventeen years. The word ויחי
vayechi means and he lived. It's interesting that the פרשה parsha about
the death of יעקב Yaakov is called ויחי, Vayechi, life. This teaches
us that a צדיק tzaddik is called living even after he passes
away. יעקב Yaakov calls his son יוסף Yosef and asks him to
swear that he will bury him in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, in
the מערת המכפלה, Me'aras Hamachpelah, with his fathers. He didn't want to
be buried in מצרים Mitzrayim because he knew that eventually מצרים Mitzrayim
would be a place of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. יוסף Yosef promises
him and יעקב Yaakov bows at the head of the bed. Later,
יעקב Yaakov becomes ill, and יוסף Yosef brings his two sons, מנשה
Menashe and אפרים, Ephraim, to receive a ברכה. bracha. יעקב Yaakov crosses
his hands and puts his right hand on אפרים, Ephraim, the younger
one, and his left hand on מנשה, Menashe, the older one. יוסף
Yosef tries to correct him, but יעקב Yaakov says, I know my
son, I know. He saw with רוח הקודש Ruach Hakodesh that great
people would come from both, but אפרים's Ephraim descendant, יהושע, Yehoshua, would
lead the יידן Yidden into the land. Then יעקב Yaakov calls all
his sons to give them their final blessings. He tells them what
will happen in the אחרית הימים. acharis hayamim. After יעקב Yaakov passes
away, the brothers are afraid that יוסף Yosef will take revenge now
that their father is gone. But יוסף Yosef comforts them and says
that even though they meant it for bad, ה' Hashem meant it
for good to save many people. The ספר sefer ends with the
death of יוסף, Yosef, who also asks to be carried back to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when the גאולה Geulah comes. We conclude the
ספר sefer by saying חזק חזק ונתחזק. Chazak Chazak V'nischazek. And let
them make Me a sanctuary that I may dwell among them. The
תורה Torah. tells us this week in פרשת תרומה, Parshas Terumah, ועשו
לי מקדש ושכנתי בתוכם. Ve'asu li mikdash veshakhanti betokham. They shall make
for Me a sanctuary and I will dwell among them. The famous
question is it should have said ושכנתי בתוכו, veshakhanti betokho, within it,
within the משכן. Mishkan. Why does it say בתוכם, betokham, within them?
The answer given is that השם Hashem dwells within every single individual
of the Jewish people. Each and every one of us has to
make ourselves a מקדש, a sanctuary for השם Hashem to dwell in.
How do we do this? By doing מצות mitzvos and learning תורה.
Torah When we do a מצוה, mitzvah, we are bringing the שכינה
into this world and into ourselves. But what if the board is
less than four טפחים tefachim wide? So, the גמרא Gemara says that's
okay. But what if you take those boards and you line them
up one next to the other? So now it looks like a
ceiling again. So, there's a מחלוקת machlokes in the גמרא Gemara whether
that's allowed or not. Whether we say that since each individual board
is less than four טפחים, tefachim, it's okay, or do we say
that since the whole thing together looks like a ceiling, it's not
okay. And then the גמרא Gemara says, what if he takes those
boards and he turns them on their side? So now the part
that's facing up is only, let's say, an inch or two wide.
So then the גמרא Gemara says that's definitely okay because it doesn't
look like a ceiling at all. A ceiling is never made of
boards that are standing on their side. And that is why it
is called the case of turning it on its side. Now, the
גמרא Gemara says that even if the boards are wider than four
טפחים, tefachim, if you turn them on their side, it's okay because
once they're on their side, they don't look like a ceiling anymore.
Now, what happens if he took these boards and he used them
not for the סכך, s'chach, but for the walls of the סוכה?
Sukkah? So, the הלכה halachah is that anything is כשר kasher for
walls. You can use any material for the walls of a סוכה.
Sukkah. You can even use a person, you can use an animal,
you can use a tree. As long as it's sturdy and it
doesn't move in the wind. So, certainly, you can use these boards
for the walls. But the problem is only for the סכך. s'chach.
Now, let's say a person has a סוכה Sukkah that's built under
a tree. Or it's built inside his house. So, the משנה Mishnah
says that's פסול. pasul. Because the תורה Torah, says you have to
sit in סוכות, Sukkos, and the חכמים chachamim, explain that it has
to be under the open sky. It can't be under a tree,
and it can't be under a roof. If there's something else between
you and the sky, other than the סכך, s'chach, then it's not
a כשר kasher סוכה. Sukkah. What if a person has a סוכה
Sukkah on top of another סוכה? Sukkah? So, the משנה Mishnah. says
that the bottom one is פסול pasul and the top one is
כשר. kasher. Why? Because the bottom one has the top סוכה Sukkah
acting as a roof over it. So, you're not sitting under the
סכך s'chach of your own סוכה, Sukkah, you're sitting under the floor
of the סוכה Sukkah above you. The starting point is that the
issue of being together with the כלל Klal is not a side
issue. It is not just a nice thing to do. It is
the very definition of what a ייד Yid is. A person who
separates himself from the ציבור, tzibur, the רמב"ם Rambam says in הלכות
תשובה Hilchot Teshuvah in the third פרק, Perek, that although he has
not done any specific עבירות, aveirot, but he says, "Who am I?
I will go my own way. What do I need the troubles
of the עם ישראל Am Yisrael for?" such a person has no
חלק chelek in the עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. This is a very
frightening thing. A person can keep all the מצוות, mitzvot, can learn
תורה, Torah but if he is a פורש מן הציבור, poresh min
hatzibur, he separates himself from the community, he has no חלק. chelek.
Why is that? Because the whole basis of our relationship with הקדוש
ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is through being a part of the
עם, Am, the nation. We find that when אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu
was told לך לך, Lech Lecha, it was not just for him
as an individual, it was to create a גוי גדול, goy gadol,
a great nation. And the תורה Torah. was given to the כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael at הר סיני Har Sinai כאיש אחד בלב אחד,
ke’ish echad belev echad, like one man with one heart. Therefore, the
connection of an individual to the רבונו של עולם Ribono Shel Olam
goes through his connection to the כלל. Klal. Now, we see this
in the תפילה. tefillah. All our תפילות tefillot are in the plural.
רפאנו, Refa'einu, ברך עלינו, Barech Aleinu, שמע קולנו. Shema Koleinu. We are
asking for the whole כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Even a person who
is alone, his תפילה tefillah should be connected to the ציבור. tzibur.
This brings us to the current situation. We are going through a
very difficult time for עם ישראל. Am Yisrael. There is a מלחמה
milchamah in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. There is a lot of suffering.
There are people who are being killed, people who are being injured,
people who are being taken as prisoners. We have to feel that
pain. We have to feel that we are part of that. There
is a story told about the צדיק tzaddik רב אריה לוין Reb
Aryeh Levin that he went to the doctor with his wife and
he said to the doctor, "Doctor, my wife's foot is hurting us."
Not "her foot is hurting her" but "her foot is hurting us."
Because they were one. And that is how we have to feel
about every single ייד. Yid. If a ייד Yid in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael is hurting, it is hurting us. It is not someone
else's problem. It is our problem. And that connection is what gives
us the strength to overcome. The גמרא Gemara says in מסכת תענית
Masechet Taanit that when the ציבור tzibur is in distress, a person
should not say, "I will go to my house and I will
eat and drink and peace be upon you, my soul." Rather, a
person should share in the distress of the community. And if he
does so, he will be זוכה zocher to see the consolation of
the community. We see this with משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. When עם
ישראל Am Yisrael were fighting with עמלק, Amalek, it says that משה
רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu sat on a stone. Why did he not sit
on a chair or a cushion? The גמרא Gemara says he said,
"Since עם ישראל Am Yisrael are in distress, I will also be
in distress." He wanted to feel the pain of the עם. Am.
And this is what is expected of us. We have to feel
the pain. We have to pray for them. We have to do
מצוות mitzvot in their merit. Every single thing we do, if we
have in mind that we are doing it for the כלל, Klal,
it has a much greater impact. It is not just an individual
act. It is an act of the whole עם ישראל. Am Yisrael.
We have to remember that הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is
with us in our distress. עמו אנכי בצרה. Imo anochi b'tzarah. He
feels our pain. And when we are united, when we feel each
other's pain, that is when we are most powerful. The שנאת חנם,
sinat chinam, the groundless hatred, that is what caused the חורבן, churban,
the destruction. And the only way to fix it is through אהבת
חנם, ahavat chinam, groundless love. To love every ייד Yid just because
they are a ייד. Yid. Because they are part of our family.
We have to look past the differences. We have to look past
the external things and see the נשמה. neshamah. Every נשמה neshamah is
a חלק אלוק ממעל, chelek Eloka mima’al, a part of השם Hashem
from above. And we are all connected at that level. So when
we strengthen that connection, we are strengthening the whole עם ישראל. Am
Yisrael. We are bringing more light into the world. And that light
will eventually dispel all the darkness. We have to have אמונה, emunah,
faith, that הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is in control. Even
when things look very dark, even when we do not understand what
is happening, we have to know that everything is directed by השגחה
פרטית, hashgacha pratit, individual divine providence. And there is a purpose to
everything. Our job is to do our part. To be the best
יידן Yidden we can be. To be more careful with our תפילה,
tefillah, to be more careful with how we treat others, to learn
more תורה. Torah Because every word of תורה Torah, creates an angel
that protects the עם ישראל. Am Yisrael. We are in a spiritual
battle as well as a physical one. And the spiritual battle is
won with the tools that the רבונו של עולם Ribono Shel Olam
gave us. The תורה, Torah the מצוות, mitzvot, the תפילה. tefillah. Let
us hope and pray that very soon we should see the end
of all the suffering. That there should be a גאולה שלמה Geulah
Sheleimah for the whole עם ישראל. Am Yisrael. That all the captives
should come home safely. That all the soldiers should be protected. That
there should be a רפואה שלמה refuah sheleimah for all the wounded.
And that we should be זוכה zocher to see the כבוד השם
Kavod Hashem revealed in the world with the coming of משיח Mashiach
במהרה בימינו, bimheirah b'yameinu, אמן. Amen. Alright let's begin the second half
of סעיף *seif* ל Lamed, *lamed* in סימן Siman *siman* ס"ט *samech
tes*. The מחבר Mechaber *mechaber* says as follows: ואם שהה בו שיעור
כבוש *ve'im shaha bo shiur kavush* if it stayed there for the
שיעור *shiur* of כבוש *kavush*, which is twenty-four hours, נאסר כולו *ne'esar
kulo* the entire piece of meat becomes forbidden. This is because of
the rule of כבוש כמבושל *kavush k'mevushal* soaking is like cooking. Since
the meat is already past the שיעור *shiur* of מליחה *melicha*, we
view this ציר *tzir* as having the status of דם *dam*. Therefore,
if it stays for twenty-four hours, it permeates and forbids the whole
piece. Then the רמ"א Rema *rama* adds: הגה *haga* והני מילי milli,
*ve-hanei milei* this is only according to the מחבר Mechaber *mechaber*. However,
ונהגו להחמיר *venahagu lehachmir* we are accustomed to be more stringent, שאפילו
לא שהה בו כלל Klall *she'afilu lo shaha bo klal* even if
it didn't stay there for any amount of time, as soon as
it touches the ציר *tzir*, נאסר כולו *ne'esar kulo* the entire piece
becomes forbidden. The reason is because we treat the ציר *tzir* exactly
like דם *dam* which forbids the meat instantly. But the רמ"א Rema
*rama* says that במקום הפסד מרובה *bimkom hefsed merubah* in a case
of significant loss or לכבוד שבת Shabbos *lichvod Shabbos* or for a
סעודת מצוה mitzvah, *seudas mitzvah*, we can be lenient and follow the
מחבר Mechaber *mechaber* that it only becomes forbidden after twenty-four hours. If
it was less than twenty-four hours, it would only require a כדי
קליפה *k'dei klipa*. Where the רמ"א Rema writes that if a person
has a thought of a woman during the day, it'll bring him
to a nocturnal emission at night. And the רמ"א Rema is bringing
this down based on the גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
דף כ' Daf Chaf עמוד א'. Amud Aleph The גמרא Gemara says
over there ונשמרת מכל דבר רע, V'nishmarta Mikol Davar Ra, and the
explanation is שלא יהרהר אדם ביום ויבוא לידי טומאה בלילה, Shelo Yeharher
Adam Bayom V'yavo Lidei Tumah Balaylah, that a person shouldn't have thoughts
during the day and come to impurity at night. Now, we see
that the מחבר Mechaber brings this in סימן Siman כ"ג Kaf Gimmel
in אבן העזר, Even Ha'ezer, and the רמ"א brings it down over
here in סימן Siman קנ"א. Kuf Nun Aleph. The question is why
is it mentioned twice? The ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan explains that in
סימן Siman כ"ג Kaf Gimmel it's talking about the prohibition of הוצאת
זרע לבטלה. Hotza'as Zera L'vatala. And over here in סימן Siman קנ"א
Kuf Nun Aleph the רמ"א is bringing it down because it's talking
about the הנהגה, Hanhagah, the way a person should behave, to be
careful even from the הרהור Hirhur itself. Even though the מחבר doesn't
mention it here, the רמ"א feels it's important to mention it in
the context of the laws of being careful with one's thoughts. Because
the הרהור Hirhur is what leads to the actual מעשה. Ma'aseh. And
we find this also in אורח חיים Orach Chaim in סימן ג'
Gimmel where the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah talks about being careful with
these things. Also we have the concept of הרהורי עבירה קשים מעבירה,
Hirhurei Aveirah Kashin Me'aveirah, thoughts of sin are harder than the sin
itself. This is because the הרהור Hirhur affects the soul more directly.
The גמרא Gemara in יומא Yoma דף כ"ט Daf Chaf Tes עמוד
amud א' says this. It means that when you're actually doing the
sin, it's just the physical part, but when you're thinking about it,
you're involving your whole mind and your spiritual essence in the transgression.
A person has to be very careful with what they look at
because ראייה, Re'iyah, seeing, leads to הרהור, Hirhur, and הרהור Hirhur leads
to מעשה. Ma'aseh. As it says, ולא תתורו אחרי לבבכם ואחרי עיניכם.
V'lo Sasuru Acharei Levavchem V'acharei Eineichem. You shouldn't stray after your heart
and after your eyes. It starts with the eyes, and then it
goes to the heart, and then it goes to the מעשה. Ma'aseh.
That's why we have to guard our eyes. And these points are
what חז"ל Chazal call the זמנים. zmanim. The זמנים zmanim are not
just arbitrary points in time, they are points where the nature of
the day changes. And once you understand the nature of the day,
then you can understand how to function within that day, how to
live within that day, how to serve the רבונו של עולם Ribono
Shel Olam within that day, because the service of the day depends
on the time of the day. Just like we have מצוות שהזמן
גרמא, mitzvos shehazman grama, commandments that are caused by time, everything we
do is in a sense caused by the time. The time dictates
what should be done. When it's morning, you do morning things, when
it's afternoon, you do afternoon things, when it's night, you do night
things. But it's not just because we decided that morning is for
this and night is for that. It's because the nature of the
morning is different than the nature of the night, and the nature
of the afternoon is different than both. And that's what we have
to understand. What is the nature of these different times and how
does that affect our עבודה, avodah, our service. We shouldn't just look
for what we are required to do, but we should look for
ways to do more, to go לפנים משורת הדין, lifnim mishuras hadin,
beyond the letter of the law, to show our love for the
רבונו של עולם. Ribono Shel Olam. The גמרא Gemara teaches us a
very important lesson in the power of a person's words. There's a
concept of ברית כרותה לשפתיים, bris kerutah lisfatayim, that a covenant is
made with the lips. Whatever a person says has the potential to
become a reality. We see this in the story of אברהם אבינו
Avraham Avinu when he told his servants, "Stay here with the donkey,
ואני והנער נלכה עד כה ונשתחוה ונשובה אליכם," v'ani vehana'ar nelchah ad
koh venishtachaveh venashuvah aleichem, "and I and the lad will go until
here, and we will prostrate ourselves and we will return to you."
Now, אברהם Avraham knew that he was going to offer יצחק Yitzchak
as a sacrifice. He didn't know yet that he wasn't going to
actually go through with it. So why did he say "we will
return"? רש״י Rashi explains that he prophesied without even realizing it. His
words had such power that they created the reality that they would
both return safely. This is why we have to be so careful
with what we say. We should never say something negative about ourselves
or about others. Because those words can become a self-fulfilling prophecy. Instead,
we should always speak words of ברכה, bracha, words of blessing, words
of encouragement. By speaking positively, we can bring more positive energy and
more positive outcomes into our lives and into the world around us.
As the פסוק Pasuk, says, "מות וחיים ביד לשון," mavet vechayim beyad
lashon, "death and life are in the power of the tongue." Let
us use our speech for good, for building, and for bringing light
into the world. We ask הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu every
day to help us in this battle. Because without him, we wouldn't
be able to stand. The גמרא Gemara in מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah
says that לעתיד לבוא, l'atid lavo, in the time to come, הקדוש
ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu brings the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara and
slaughters it in front of the צדיקים tzaddikim and the רשעים. reshaim.
To the צדיקים, tzaddikim, it looks like a mountain, and to the
רשעים, reshaim, it looks like a hair. Both of them cry. The
צדיקים tzaddikim cry and say, how were we able to conquer such
a high mountain? And the רשעים reshaim cry and say, how were
we not able to conquer such a small hair? This is a
very famous גמרא Gemara in מסכת סוכה, Masechet Sukkah, דף נב. Daf
Nun Bais. The point is that when you fight the יצר הרע,
Yetzer Hara, you see its true size. You realize how difficult the
struggle is. But when you give in, it seems like nothing. It
seems easy to change, but you never do. The goal of an
עובד, oved, of someone who is working on themselves, is to realize
that even if it looks like a mountain, with the help of
שמיים, shamayim, we can overcome it. We have to realize that the
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara is only as strong as we allow it
to be through our lack of effort. But once we engage in
the מלחמה, milchama, the war, we see the true magnitude of our
accomplishments. And then נתיישבה דעתו, nityashva da'ato, משה Moshe felt at ease.
And then the גמרא Gemara says that משה Moshe said to the
הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam,
you have such a man, why are you giving the תורה Torah,
through me? Why not give it through him? הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh
Baruch Hu replied, שתוק כך עלה במחשבה לפני, shetok kach ala be-machshava
lefanai, be silent, for such is My decree. משה Moshe then said,
רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, you have shown me his תורה,
Torah now show me his reward. הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu
said, turn around. משה Moshe turned around and saw them weighing his
flesh in the butcher shop. משה Moshe cried out, רבונו של עולם,
Ribono Shel Olam, זו תורה וזו שכרה? zu Torah ve-zu secharah? This
is תורה Torah and this is its reward? הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh
Baruch Hu replied again, שתוק כך עלה במחשבה לפני. shetok kach ala
be-machshava lefanai. This story is very profound. It tells us that while
we can understand the הלכות and the logic of the תורה Torah
on one level, there is a deeper level, a level of מחשבה,
machshava, that is beyond our grasp. The תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al
peh is the bridge between our world and that divine thought. This
is what we celebrate on שבועות. Shavuos. We celebrate the link that
connects us to the infinite. When we stand at הר סיני Har
Sinai every year, we renew that connection. We say נעשה ונשמע, na'aseh
ve-nishma, accepting the תורה Torah. even the parts we don't fully understand.
This is the essence of being a member of the עם ישראל.
Am Yisrael. We are a people defined by our commitment to ה׳
Hashem and His תורה. Torah, We spend the night of שבועות Shavuos
learning, staying awake to show our eagerness for קבלת התורה. Kabbalat HaTorah.
This process of learning and growing never ends. It continues in every
בית מדרש Beis Medrash and in every Jewish home. Each of us
has a portion in the תורה, Torah and it is our job
to find it and to live it. May we all be זוכה
zocher to receive the תורה Torah with joy and with a full
heart. משנכנסו לארץ לא הוכשרו כל הארצות לומר שירה. mishenichnasu la'aretz lo
huchsharu kol ha'aratzot lomar shira. Once we entered Israel, other lands were
no longer fitting. Then the גמרא Gemara gives another answer. רב נחמן
אמר, Rav Nachman amar, קריאתה זו היא הלילא. kriatah zu hi Halela.
The reading of the מגילה Megillah itself is the saying of הלל.
Hallel. Then רבא אמר, Rava amar, בשלמא התם הללו עבדי ה׳ ולא
עבדי פרעה. bishlama hatam halelu avdei Hashem velo avdei Pharaoh. In Egypt,
we could say praise the servants of ה׳ Hashem and not the
servants of פרעה. Pharaoh. הכא הללו עבדי ה׳ ולא עבדי אחשורוש? hacha
halelu avdei Hashem velo avdei Achashverosh? Can we say that here? אכתי
עבדי אחשורוש אנן. akti avdei Achashverosh anan. We are still the servants
of אחשורוש. Achashverosh. We're still in גלות. galus. So these are the
three answers the גמרא Gemara gives. Some say Mr. Happy had a
bit of an ice bucket challenge play before, and just how messy
it would be, pushed him over the edge. I've murdered him. It
was an overreaction. I should have listened to my neighbor lady. She
tried to tell me, but no. I didn't mean to murder my
best friend. I'm a terrible, terrible person and I need to be
punished. I like how there was a neighbor who was also like,
help, I'm being murdered, help! No, go away! No! Do you need
help? Help! No, go away! No! Do you need help? Police said
Jaylo was extremely intoxicated and was shocked when they told him they
could not charge him with involuntary manslaughter for his roommate. Police took
Jaylo into custody and began to search Gaylord's house where they found
drug paraphernalia and a machine gun. When they went down, I like
how it happened. That's my favorite. When they went down and found
a body in the backyard. And then they went up to Chris
Gaylord and was like, was that the real Mr. Happy? Was that
the real person? He said, yes. It was like the reverse M.
Night Shyamalan at the end. And everyone was like, you crazy bastard
friend. And then when they dug him up at the end, there
was a guy named Mr. Happy. He had found a body or
something and his name was like, like Scoundrel Happy. And he built
some kind of machine, he was building a therapist out of him.
Like oh my god, he was building a therapist. Oh my god,
that would be a crazy twist. Oh no, you know what would
be even better? Mr. Happy, Adolf Hitler. When they found the body
it was Adolf Hitler. And just yeah, and the guy killed Hitler
and they're like, what do we do? What do we do now?
And he's a hero, with a Purple Heart. I give you a
Medal of Honor. Medal of Honor. Like in the Call of Duty
game they named after him because he took out Mr. Happy. That
was amazing, that was an amazing twist. He died in anonymity and
they're like, oh no, you just killed Happy sure, and then they
actually find the body, it's Adolf Hitler. Oh my god, that was
blow mind. That would be so blow mind. I'm sorry, I just
went into a fantasy for a second. Alright, let's go. Let's go
to some step dad or step mom house at driving out there.
Howdy, welcome back Jacksons, Prisoners of War. Hey, did you know? Oh
yeah, it's the fall, it's the best time of year. Straight in
my mouth. I remember when, I probably, I mean חנוכה, Hanukkah, everyone
חנוכה, Hanukkah, I remember when Halloween had ended and the next person
for Christmas everybody now it was like, no, we're still two major
holidays away, for now, thinking about the month of December. We have
four months before Christmas. Imagine someone like starting pre-gaming for Christmas four
months early. Like, what are you saying, you're all fine to start
pre-gaming for Christmas like literally, yeah, it's already, there's something about Christmas,
it's a little rock. December gives me you. That's the point. That's
all I'm saying. Yeah, happy חנוכה, Hanukkah, happy חנוכה Hanukkah to you
my friend. Yeah, it's our סדר, Seder, so it's something personal, a
little bit היימיש. heimish. That's for us. That's the point. Yeah, the
היימישness. heimish It's היימיש, heimish, right? Exactly. The Zoom סיום. Siyum. Okay,
the Zoom סיום. Siyum. The Zoom סיום. Siyum. That's why we like
the Zoom סיום. Siyum. That was everything. Making the Zoom סיום. Siyum.
Yeah, the Zoom סיום Siyum thing started. Yeah. Tokyo Ichiba? Tokyo something.
Place downtown. Yeah. The fake Japanese food. Yeah, fake Japanese. Place downtown.
Yeah, Panda Express. Oh yeah, but it's like they cook the chicken
in front of you. Yeah, exactly. So I went to that and
then I saw a place next door called Panda Express. I was
like I should have tried that. I should have went to the
fake Tokyo. Wait what happened? First I went to Panda Express before...
Nando's? Panda Express is Nando's? Yeah. Panda Express is Nando's? Yeah. Every
time I was like Panda Express is delicious. I'm like you have
the standards of a person who loves Panda Express. I like Panda
Express way too much. I think I like it way too much.
I would rather go to Jim's Wok, this little hole in the
wall place run by people who don't speak any English and it's
basically the best. That's true. But a place Nando's. Nando's is on
every other block all over this country. Oh, it was some place
like that, one of those chain places. They use סיני Sini and
give you free egg rolls. Yes! Yes, that's right! You get סיני
Sini and an egg roll! I hate those egg rolls. Right? What's
wrong with you? Yeah, that's what I was thinking. The Panda Express
was really bad. That was bad Panda Express. It was a bad
Panda Express. It was a bad Panda Express. It was the top
Chinese place or something. And you go there, that's the noodle, the
branch of Spaghetti Shop. Terrible. Terrible. I went to this place, I
looked it up, and it was the first place that had one
star with thirty people. And I was like, yeah. That reminds me
of when we went to Ebisu two years ago, one year ago,
whenever it was, and the Japanese restaurant, and everyone was like, "Oh
my god, this place looks so cool, we should go in there
one day." From the outside, it looked amazing. We go in, we
sit down. We should have known. It was 7 PM and no
one was in there but us. We were like, "Oh, yeah, no,
I guess people come in later then." They proceeded to... first of
all, I posted a picture on their Yelp review where I gave
them one star because myself and the other person at the table
ordered the same thing. It came out on two different dishes. Then
everything we ordered came out in different dimensions. So one person got
their food first, and then five minutes, two other people, and then
fifteen minutes for three other people, and then finally one person got
their food. It was like, there's no one here! Are you cooking
them one at a time? There's no one here! How many burners
you got back there? One? You cooking them on the rack like
a little camping stove? I was so mad. Oh, I left so
angry at that place. I think the worst restaurant I've ever been
to. While we were at the restaurant, I looked up the Yelp
review and it just said, "Worst restaurant I've ever been to. This
place is a waste of space." Oh yeah. It was like a...
I'll check what it said. I remember that Yelp review it was
like... yeah, no. Telling everyone to f-off. f-off. To f-off and then
the restaurant. I didn't say that. It just said f-m. Basically f-m.
But I did find Nando's. I found something cool in California that
I was all about Nando's. Yeah, there's a fake Nando's. It's a
fake Nando's called Porto's? Porto's? Porto's? Porto's. Porto's is in California and
it's in Burbank. Every time I drive through Burbank, there's a big
line for this place. It's because even though it's a fake, it
looks like they stole Nando's' graphics. Which I'm okay with. If it
tastes even remotely close, I'll be okay with it. Oh, I learned
something. I learned that Chicago actually has Nando's. What? Yeah, it's got
4.8 out of 5 stars. Nando's Peri-Peri. It's another one opening in
Chicago too, and I missed it. I missed a good one. I
should have gone to a good one. Well, enough food talk. Let's
play some sport talk. We have something that the fans, the listeners,
wanted to know. We finally have some information. Here it is. By
Lauren Evans, "I went to Westfield, New Jersey to track down the
Watcher." All right. Lauren Evans went to Westfield, New Jersey. Here it
is. Six fifty seven Boulevard. Wow. Okay. Let's see. It's a beautiful
house. It's really big. It's got a big lawn. Okay. That's it.
I recall many many years ago, maybe thirty or forty years ago,
a certain person came to my house and I bought from him
a ספר Sefer called עבודת הגרשוני Avodat HaGershuni by גרשון אשכנזי, Gershon
Ashkenazi, the famous רב Rav? of Metz. He has a שו"ת Shut
there in יורה דעה, Yoreh De'ah, סימן מ"ג. Siman Mem Gimmel. And
he speaks there about a problem that occurred in Metz, that the
גבאי—the Gabbai גבאים—they Gabbaim needed to have לחם—fresh lechem לחם—on lechem the
second day of יום טוב Yom Tov for the people, and for
מוצאי יום טוב. Motzei Yom Tov. So they had a גוי Goy
that baked for them. He was like a חלה Challah baker for
the community. This גוי—his Goy name was עמי. Ami. And this is
what happened in Metz many many years ago. רבן גמליאל אומר Rabban
Gamliel omer חולין chulin נאכל ne'echal כל ארבע arba ותרומה u'terumah כל
חמש chamesh ושורפין u'sorfin בתחילת b'techilat שש. shesh. This completes the three
opinions of the משנה. Mishnah. We had רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
said one eats it all five שעות sha'ot and burns it at
the sixth. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you eat all four,
you wait the fifth, and you burn at the sixth. And רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who says חולין chulin is eaten for four and
תרומה terumah is eaten for five. And everybody agrees you burn at
the sixth. Now the גמרא Gemara starts on דף י"ד עמוד א'.
Daf Yud Dalet Amud Aleph. And it brings the next part of
the משנה. Mishnah אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina סגן הכהנים Segan
HaKohanim מימיהם של כהנים mi'meihem shel Kohanim לא נמנעו מלשרוף את הבשר
שנטמא בוולד הטומאה lo nimneu mil'sorof et habasar shenitma b'velad hatumah עם
הבשר שנטמא באב הטומאה im habasar shenitma b'av hatumah אף על פי
שמוסיפין טומאה על טומאתו. af al pi she'mosifin tumah al tumato. This
means the priests were allowed to take meat of a lighter impurity
and burn it with meat of a higher impurity, even though it
made the first meat more impure. Why? Because it's going to be
burned anyway. הוסיף רבי עקיבא Hosif Rabbi Akiva ואמר ve'amar מימיהם של
כהנים mi'meihem shel Kohanim לא נמנעו מלהדליק את השמן שנפסל בטבול יום
lo nimneu mil'hadlik et hashemen shenifsal b'tevul yom בנר שנטמא בטמא מת
b'ner shenitma b'tamei met אף על פי שמוסיפין טומאה על טומאתו. af
al pi she'mosifin tumah al tumato. Again, the same concept. You take
oil that is a פסול pasul and you put it in a
lamp that is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. This makes the oil
more impure, but since it's going to be burned, it's allowed. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir learn
from this? He says מדבריהם למדנו midivreihem lamadnu ששורפין תרומה טהורה עם
תרומה טמאה בפסח. she'sorfin terumah tehorah im terumah tmeiah b'Pesach. He says
we can learn from the כהנים Kohanim that on the 14th of
ניסן, Nissan, we can burn pure תרומה terumah together with impure תרומה.
terumah. Even though we're making the pure one impure, it's going to
be burned anyway so it doesn't matter. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says אמר לו רבי יוסי Amar lo Rabbi Yossi אינה היא המידה.
eino hi hamidah. This is not a proper comparison. Why? Because the
meat and the oil were already impure, you're just increasing the level.
But the pure תרומה terumah is not impure yet. It's only forbidden
because of the time. So you shouldn't be allowed to make it
impure. Now the גמרא Gemara starts analyzing the details. What exactly is
the increase in impurity? The גמרא Gemara explains that we have different
levels: אב הטומאה, av hatumah, ראשון, rishon, שני. sheni. Meat that is
a וולד הטומאה velad hatumah is a שני. sheni. If you touch
it to an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, it becomes a ראשון. rishon.
That's an increase. What about the oil? The oil was a פסול
pasul from a טבול יום. tevul yom. If you put it in
a lamp that is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, it becomes a
ראשון. rishon. How is the lamp an אב הטומאה? av hatumah? Because
of the rule חרב הרי הוא כחלל. cherev harei hu ke'chalal. A
metal vessel that touches a dead body becomes an אב הטומאה. av
hatumah. So the lamp is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, and the
oil becomes a ראשון. rishon. So we see they were increasing the
impurity. Then the גמרא Gemara gets into a discussion about liquids. Are
liquids impure מן התורה min haTorah or מדרבנן? mi'derabbanan? Some say it's
only rabbinic. If it's only rabbinic, then increasing the impurity is a
smaller issue. But if it's from the Torah, it's a bigger issue.
The גמרא Gemara brings proofs from various פסוקים pesukim like וכל משקה
אשר ישתה. v'chol mashkeh asher yishateh. The conclusion of the גמרא Gemara
is that regardless of whether it's Torah or rabbinic, the כהנים Kohanim
showed that something destined for destruction can be treated more leniently. And
that's the logic רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir uses for burning the חמץ.
chametz. He says that once the time of the prohibition arrives, the
pure תרומה terumah is also essentially on its way to being burned,
so it's okay to burn it with the impure תרומה terumah and
make it impure in the process. This is the main part of
the discussion on דף י"ד Daf Yud Dalet and דף ט"ו Daf
Tes Vav regarding the laws of טומאה as they relate to the
burning of the חמץ. chametz. What's the difference between bread and wine?
Bread you eat like it is. The grain is harvested, ground, and
baked into bread. Wine, on the other hand, is mixed, and that
is תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al peh. It is the mixing of
different sources, of different סברות, s'varot, of different ideas to reach a
conclusion. The Rebbe says an amazing שיחה Sichah in חלק כ' Chelek
Chof פרשת בא Parshas Bo where the Rebbe talks about the concept
of bringing the גאולה Geulah and the Rebbe asks why does the
Torah use the language of בא Bo instead of לך? Lech? Come
to Pharaoh instead of go to Pharaoh. And the זוהר Zohar explains
that it was because משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was afraid. He was
afraid to go into the palace of Pharaoh alone. So השם Hashem
says to him בא, Bo, come with me. Come into the room
of the king. And the Rebbe explains that in a deeper level,
this is how we have to approach the world. We don't go
into the world alone. We go with the strength of the רבי.
Rebbe. We go with the strength of the אייבערשטער. Aibershter. And when
we realize that we are just שלוחים shluchim and we're just doing
a שליחות, shlichus, then we have the power to overcome all the
obstacles. Because Pharaoh, which represents the source of all the קליפות, kelipos,
even there, השם Hashem is present. בא Bo means come with me,
because השם Hashem is already there. אין עוד מלבדו. Ain Od Milvado.
There's nothing besides for השם. Hashem. So when we go to transform
the world and to make a דירה בתחתונים, Dira Btachtonim, a dwelling
place for השם Hashem in this physical world, we should know that
השם Hashem is with us and the רבי Rebbe is with us.
And this is how we're going to bring משיח. Moshiach. And it
should happen speedily in our days, אמן. Amen. We learned in מסכת
גיטין Masechet Gittin that we are dealing with the laws of a
גט. get. In the eighth פרק, perek, the משנה mishna discusses various
scenarios where the validity of the divorce document is questioned. On דף
Daf, ע ayin עמוד Amud, ב, bet, the גמרא Gemara introduces the
concept of a person who is seized by a קורדייקוס. kordeikus. This
condition, as explained by the חכמים, Chachamim involves a temporary loss of
דעת, da'at, or mental faculty, often due to physical causes. If a
man tells others to write a גט get for his wife while
in this state, we do not act upon his words because he
lacks the required כוונה, kavanah, or intent, which is a fundamental requirement
for the divorce process to be binding according to the הלכה. halacha.
The גמרא Gemara explains that only if he gave the instructions before
the onset of the condition do we fulfill his request after he
recovers. This illustrates the absolute necessity for a person to be in
a sound state of mind when performing a legal act of such
consequence. The הלכה halacha is very careful to protect the status of
an אשת איש, eishet ish, a married woman, and to ensure that
a גט get is only given through a process of clear, conscious
will. The רמב"ם Rambam and other פוסקים poskim further clarify that even
if the man eventually recovers, his words during the time of his
illness have no legal standing. This סוגיא sugya teaches us about the
intersection of physical health and legal responsibility in the framework of תורה
Torah law, highlighting the precision with which the גמרא Gemara treats every
individual situation. But what happens if you're not able to get a
hold of your רב? Rav In that case, you should follow the
general principle of ספק דרבנן לקולא, safek d'rabonon l'kula, ספק דאורייתא לחומרא.
safek d'oraisa l'humra. If a person is told to do something, he's
a שליח, shaliach, he can't then turn around and tell somebody else
to be the שליח shaliach because words cannot be handed over. So
why over here are we allowed to have a שליח עושה שליח?
shaliach ose shaliach? Why is the second person valid? The גמרא Gemara
answers, it's different because over here he's handing over the physical גט.
get. Since he's handing over the חפצא, cheftza, the object, that's not
called מילי, that's not just words. Since there is a physical object
involved, the שליחות shelichus can be transferred. This is the basic יסוד
yesod of the סוגיא. sugya. The גמרא Gemara in מסכת בבא קמא,
Masechet Bava Kamma, דף כ"ג, Daf Chof Gimmel, עמוד ב', discusses a
very interesting מחשבה. Machshava. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, משפיכין Mashpichin
are חייב. Chayav. And רש"י Rashi says over there on the עמוד,
that the reason why they're חייב Chayav is because it's like a
בור. Bor. And when a person pours water into the רשות הרבים,
Reshus HaRabim, and it causes someone to slip, he's basically creating a
מפגע. Mifga. But תוספות Tosafos on the דף, daf דיבור המתחיל Dibbur
Hamaschil משפיכין, Mashpichin, has a different approach. תוספות says that the whole
reason they are חייב Chayav is because it's considered אדם המזיק. Adam
Hamazik. And because we have a כלל that אדם מועד לעולם, Adam
Muad Le'olam, whether he did it accidentally or he did it on
purpose, whether he was ער Er or he was ישן, Yashen, he's
going to be חייב. Chayav. This is a very fundamental יסוד Yesod
in the דינים Dinim of נזיקין. Nezikin. And it's something that we
have to be very careful with, especially in a place where people
are walking, to make sure that we're not creating any kind of
מכשול Michshol for another person. However, we have another שיטה, shita, the
שיטה shita of רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says
that there are two שקיעות. shki'os. There's the first שקיעה shki'ah and
the second שקיעה. shki'ah. The first שקיעה shki'ah is when the sun
disappears from our sight, and the second שקיעה shki'ah is much later,
close to צאת הכוכבים. tzeis hakochavim. According to רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam,
בין השמשות bein hashmashos only begins after the second שקיעה. shki'ah. This
מחלוקת machlokes is very important for understanding when שבת Shabbos, starts and
ends. Most of the עולם olam today follows the שיטה shita of
the גאונים, Geonim, which is that שקיעה shki'ah is the beginning of
בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. But there are many who are מחמיר machmir
like רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, especially for the end of שבת, Shabbos,
to wait until seventy-two minutes after שקיעה. shki'ah. No discernible speech was
detected in the audio file. And we see that the גמרא Gemara
says in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot that a person should always be
careful in the תפילה Tefillah of מנחה Mincha for we find that
אליהו Eliyahu was only answered in the תפילה Tefillah of מנחה. Mincha.
The גמרא Gemara explains that because מנחה Mincha is in the middle
of the day, it is a time when people are most distracted
by their worldly concerns. To stop everything and daven with כוונה Kavanah
shows that a person truly values his connection to the רבונו של
עולם. Ribono Shel Olam. We must be very careful not to let
the day pass without this important תפילה, Tefillah, as it is a
time of עת רצון Et Ratzon for all of כלל ישראל. Klal
Yisrael. In the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachos it says בצלאל Bezalel
knew how to join the אותיות Osiyos with which שמים Shamayim and
ארץ Aretz were created. משה Moshe said to him: make an ארון,
Aron, and כלים, Keilim, and a משכן. Mishkan. בצלאל Bezalel said to
him: משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, the way of the world is that
a person builds a בית Bayis and then he makes the כלים.
Keilim. If I make the כלים Keilim first, where will I put
them? משה Moshe said to him: בצל אל היית, B'tzel El Hayisa,
you were in the shadow of the Almighty and you knew. Although
the command started with the כלים Keilim because of their חשיבות, Chashivus,
in the actual מעשה, Ma'aseh, the משכן Mishkan came first. The משכן
Mishkan was finished on the twenty-fifth of כסלו Kislev but was only
set up on the first of ניסן. Nissan. This shows the מחשבה
Machshava versus the מעשה Ma'aseh and the השראת השכינה. Hashra'as HaShechina. The
world stands on three things: על התורה, Al haTorah, on the Torah,
ועל העבודה, v'al ha'avodah, on the service of God, ועל גמילות חסדים,
v'al gemilut chasadim, and on acts of loving kindness. In the תורה
Torah everything is either a המשך hemshech or a דבר חדש. davar
chadash. A המשך hemshech is a continuation, and a דבר חדש davar
chadash is something brand new. And the truth is, really, everything is
both. It's a המשך hemshech because it's all part of one big
piece, like we say that the whole תורה Torah is one long
name of הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. But it's also a
דבר חדש davar chadash because every single thing is a world unto
itself. Every letter, every word, is its own separate thing. When a
person is learning, he needs to have both of these. He needs
to have the המשך hemshech of what he learned before, to know
that it's all part of one מסורה. mesorah. But at the same
time, it has to be a דבר חדש. davar chadash. He has
to feel that it's something that is being revealed to him right
now. בכל יום יהיו בעיניך כחדשים. bechol yom yihiyu be'einecha kachadashim. Every
single day it should be like new. This balance is what gives
a person חיות chayut in his learning. The גמרא Gemara in ברכות
Brachot on דף יג daf yud gimel goes into detail about the
concept of כוונה. kavanah. Is it necessary to have intent when performing
a מצוה, mitzvah, or is the act itself sufficient? This is a
major question in the world of הלכה. halacha. The גמרא Gemara asks,
does a person fulfill their obligation if they do not have כוונה?
kavanah? This leads into a larger discussion about whether מצות צריכות כוונה.
mitzvot tzerichot kavanah. We see that the discussion centers on the phrase
היה קורא בתורה. Hayah koreh batorah. If a person was reading the
תורה Torah, and the time for שמע arrived, the משנה Mishnah states
that if he focused his heart, he has fulfilled the requirement. The
רבנים rabbonim analyze what it means to focus the heart. Does it
mean to have the intent of the מצוה, mitzvah or does it
mean to understand the words of the פסוקים? pesukim? This מחלוקת machloket
is fundamental to our understanding of how we approach our daily תפילה
tefillah and our relationship with the רבונו של עולם. Ribbono Shel Olam.
Hi everybody. Today is Tuesday, the first day of the month of
כסלו. Kislev. I guess we call it the second day of ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Today, I'm going to learn with you part of
פרשת ויצא. Parashat Vayetze. In the beginning of the פרשה, Parsha, we
learn about יעקב Yaakov leaving his home where he lived with his
parents, and he's going away to work and to hide from his
brother עשו. Esav. And in the beginning of the פרשה, Parsha, we
find a famous פסוק, Pasuk a very important פסוק Pasuk, that has
to do with how the הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu watches
over us. And in this פסוק, Pasuk the הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh
Baruch Hu tells יעקב Yaakov אבינו, Avinu, והנה אנכי עמך ושמרתיך בכל
אשר תלך. VeHineh Anochi Imcha U'Shmarticha BeChol Asher Telech. Meaning, and look,
I am with you, and I will watch over you wherever you
go. This פסוק Pasuk, is very important. It teaches us about שמירה,
Shemira, protection. Whenever we go somewhere, we know that the הקדוש ברוך
הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is with us and he is watching over
us. Many times when we are in the car, or when we
are walking somewhere, or when we are even just going to sleep,
we should remember this פסוק, pasuk and we should remember that the
הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is always with us. And he
is protecting us. In the תורה, Torah. there are many, many lessons
that we learn, and this is just one of the lessons from
this week's פרשה. Parsha. So let's remember: והנה אנכי עמך ושמרתיך בכל
אשר תלך. VeHineh Anochi Imcha U'Shmarticha BeChol Asher Telech. The הקדוש ברוך
הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is always with us. Wishing you all a
good day. שלום. Shalom. The גמרא Gemara in ברכות Brachos on דף
מ' Daf Mem says, and it's also brought down in the שלחן
ערוך Shulchan Aruch in סימן קס"א, Siman Kof-Samech-Aleph, כל הפוסל בטבילה פוסל
בנטילה. Kol haposel b'tevilah posel b'netilah. That means anything that's a פסול
Pasul because of a חציצה Chatzitzah regarding טבילה Tevilah is also going
to be a פסול Pasul when it comes to נטילת ידים. Netilat
Yadayim. However, we're going to see that there is one major difference
between חציצה Chatzitzah by טבילה Tevilah and חציצה Chatzitzah by נטילת ידים.
Netilat Yadayim. And that is, by נטילת ידים, Netilat Yadayim, only the
part of the hand that you're required to wash needs to be
free of any חציצה. Chatzitzah. If you have a חציצה Chatzitzah on
a part of your hand that's not required to be washed, it's
not a problem. However, by טבילה, Tevilah, your whole body needs to
be in the water, so if there's a חציצה Chatzitzah anywhere on
your body, it's a problem. So the first thing we have to
define is what is the part of the hand that needs to
be washed? What's the שיעור? What's the area? The שלחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch says in סימן קס"א Siman Kof-Samech-Aleph סעיף ד' Seif Dalet that
the area that needs to be washed is until the פרק. Perek.
The word פרק Perek means a joint. The question is which joint?
Is it the joint of the fingers where the fingers meet the
palm, or is it the joint of the wrist where the hand
meets the arm? The מחבר over here in סעיף ד' Seif Dalet
says clearly it's the connection between the hand and the arm, which
we call the wrist. The משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah explains that if
you only wash until the fingers, it's not enough; you must wash
the entire hand until the wrist. Therefore, any חציצה Chatzitzah that's anywhere
on the hand from the fingertips until the wrist is going to
be a problem. The מצוה mitzvah. of פרו ורבו p'ru ur'vu is
a very important מצוה. mitzvah. We see in מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot
that there's a מחלוקת machloket between בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל. Beit Hillel. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you need שני זכרים,
shnei zcharim, two sons, and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you need
a זכר ונקבה. zachar u'nekeivah. The הלכה follows בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
However, there is an additional obligation from the נביא Navi of לשבת
יצרה, lashevet yetzarah, and also from קהלת Kohelet of לערב אל תנח
ידך. la'erev al tanach yadecha. This means even if you've fulfilled the
basic obligation, you should continue to have children if possible. There's a
famous story of the תנא Tanna בן עזאי Ben Azzai who never
married. He said נפשי חשקה בתורה, nafshi chashikah baTorah, my soul yearns
for the תורה. Torah. The רמב"ם Rambam rules in הלכות אישות Hilchot
Ishut that if someone is truly like בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, they
don't have to marry. But the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch in אבן
העזר Even HaEzer says this only applies if his יצר yetzer doesn't
bother him. Most people are required to marry to keep themselves holy
and fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah Hello and welcome to the שיעור. We
are learning מסכת סוכה, Masechet Sukkah, דף יב עמוד א. daf yud
bet amud aleph. The משנה Mishna says: העושה סוכתו תחת האילן כאילו
עשאה בתוך הבית. Ha'oseh sukkato tachat ha'ilan, k'ilu asayah b'toch ha'bayit. If
one makes his סוכה sukkah under a tree, it is as if
he made it inside the house. We learned in the גמרא Gemara
in פסחים דף קי''ד kuf yud daled עמוד ב regarding the requirement
of שתי תבשילין shtei tavshilin at the סדר. Seder. The גמרא Gemara
asks מאי שתי תבשילין? mai shtei tavshilin? What are these two cooked
foods? אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: סילקא וארוזא, silka v'aruza, beets
and rice. רבא הוה קא דייק אדרב הונא. Rava hava ka dayek
a'Rav Huna. Rava was precise in his understanding of Rav Huna. מדאמר
רב הונא ארוזא, Mid'amar Rav Huna aruza, since Rav Huna specifically mentioned
rice, מכלל דאורזא לאו מינא דבשרא הוא, michlal d'oruza lav mina d'bisra
hu, it implies that rice is not a species of meat. Therefore,
even something that isn't meat can fulfill the requirement of שתי תבשילין.
shtei tavshilin. One is a זכר לפסח zecher l'Pesach and one is
a זכר לחגיגה. zecher l'chagigah. We also have the view of חזקיה.
Chizkiyah. חזקיה אמר: Chizkiyah amar: אפילו דג וביצה שעליו, afilu dag v'beitzah
she'alav, even a fish and the egg that is on it can
count as the two foods. The גמרא Gemara says in מסכת ברכות,
Masechet Brachot, כל העונה אמן אחר ברכותיו הרי זה בור. Kol ha'oneh
amen achar birchotav harei zeh bor. Someone who answers אמן amen after
his own ברכות brachot is an ignoramus. רש״י Rashi explains that it
is because it looks like he is finishing his ברכות brachot and
he is not really paying attention. But wait a minute, we find
that in ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, at the end of בונה ירושלים,
Boneh Yerushalayim, we do say אמן. amen. So the גמרא Gemara asks,
how can this be? If someone who says אמן amen after his
own ברכות brachot is a בור, bor, why do we say it
there? The answer the גמרא Gemara gives is that there is a
difference between a single ברכה bracha and a series of ברכות. brachot.
When you have a series of ברכות brachot and you want to
show where one section ends and another begins, you can say אמן.
amen. In ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, the first three ברכות brachot are
דאורייתא, de'oraita, they are from the תורה. Torah The fourth ברכה, bracha,
הטוב והמטיב, Hatov Vehameitiv, was added later by the חכמים Chachamim in
יבנה. Yavne. Therefore, we say אמן amen at the end of בונה
ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim to make a הפסק, hefsek, a distinction, to show
that the biblical section has concluded and the rabbinic section is starting.
Today we will be discussing the category of מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס.
muktzeh machmat chisron kis. This refers to an item that is set
aside because of the financial loss that might occur if it is
used for something other than its intended purpose. A person is usually
very careful with such an item and designates a specific place for
it. Examples would be a special knife used for שחיטה shechita or
a knife used for מילה. milah. These items are strictly forbidden to
move on שבת, Shabbos even if you need it לצורך גופו, l'tzorech
gufo, for its own use, or לצורך מקומו, l'tzorech mekomo, for the
space it occupies. The גמרא Gemara discusses the various opinions of the
תנאים Tannaim on this matter. We find that the timing of the
evening שמע is a subject of great discussion. Why? Because the transition
from day to night is not instantaneous. This period, known as בין
השמשות, bein hashmashos, is a time of doubt, ספק. safek. Is it
day or is it night? This affects many areas of הלכה. For
example, if a child is born during this time, when is the
ברית מילה? bris milah? Or when does שבת Shabbos. begin? The חכמים
provide clear guidelines, but the essence remains that we must approach these
times with קדושה kedushah. and awareness. The משנה Mishna uses the example
of the כהנים Kohanim to anchor this spiritual obligation in a physical
reality. When they return to a state of טהרה to eat their
תרומה, terumah, it marks a significant shift, not just for them, but
for the entire community. It teaches us that our daily actions and
our connection to the בורא עולם Borei Olam are deeply intertwined with
the natural cycles of the world around us. Okay, so we're starting
a new series. We're going to start learning together the משנה ברורה
Mishnah Berurah on הלכות ברכות, Hilchos Brachos, specifically starting from סימן רב,
Siman Reish Beis, which is the laws of ברכת הפירות, Birkas Hapeiros,
the blessings over fruits. And the מחבר writes in the beginning of
סימן רב: Siman Reish Beis: על פירות האילן הוא מברך בורא פרי
העץ. Al peiros ha'ilan hu mevarech borei pri ha'etz. Besides for the
general rule which is mentioned in the גמרא Gemara in ברכות, Brachos,
that any fruit which is... how is it considered a fruit of
the tree? We look at the tree itself, whether the גזע, geza,
the trunk, remains from year to year. If the גזע geza remains,
then it's considered an אילן, ilan, a tree. If the גזע geza
does not remain and it grows back every year from the ground,
then it is considered as an עשב, esev, a herb or a
grass. And therefore the ברכה bracha would be בורא פרי האדמה. borei
pri ha'adama. Now, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah brings down over here
in סעיף קטן א, Seif Kattan Aleph, that what is the definition
of a fruit of the tree? So he
says that if the ענפים, anafim, the branches, also
remain from year to year, then definitely it
is considered an אילן. ilan. But even if only
the גזע geza remains, and every year new branches
grow out of that trunk, it's still considered
an אילן. ilan. However, if the whole thing dies
down to the ground, and even the trunk
doesn't stay, but it grows back from the
שורשים, shorashim, from the roots, then it's considered as
an עשב, esev, and the ברכה bracha is אדמה. Adama. This
is a very important יסוד yesod because there are
many types of bushes and shrubs, like raspberries
or blueberries, which we have to determine what
their status is. So the rule is: does
the trunk stay? And the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah adds,
it's not enough that the trunk stays, it
has to be that the trunk produces the
leaves. If the leaves come out of the
ground, then it's not a tree. This is
why there's a big discussion about bananas. Since
the banana tree looks like a tree, but
actually the whole thing dies every year, therefore
the ברכה bracha on a banana is האדמה. Ha'adama. Let's
look further in the משנה ברורה. Mishnah Berurah. He brings
down that even if the tree is very
small, if it has the properties of an
אילן, ilan, then the ברכה bracha is העץ. Ha'etz. But we
have a rule: ספק ברכות להקל. Safek brachos l'hakel. Whenever we're
in doubt whether something is a tree or
not, since the ברכה bracha of האדמה Ha'adama covers everything,
it's safer to say האדמה Ha'adama in a case
of doubt. Because העץ Ha'etz is specific to trees,
whereas האדמה Ha'adama includes everything that grows from the
ground. So if someone said האדמה Ha'adama on a
fruit, he is יצא. yotzei. He has fulfilled his
obligation. But if someone said העץ Ha'etz on a
vegetable, he is not יצא. yotzei. Therefore, in any
case of uncertainty, we prefer to say האדמה.
Ha'adama. We will stop here for today and
continue next time. Thank you. There is a
very famous רמב"ם Rambam at the end of הלכות
מקואות. Hilchos Mikvaos. He asks, how does water purify? It
is a גזירת הכתוב. Gezeiras hakatuv. But he says there
is a רמז Remez here. Just like someone who
immerses in water becomes pure, someone who immerses
his soul in the waters of דעת, Da'as, of
knowledge and understanding, is purified from bad thoughts
and bad traits. He writes, וכן מי שכוון
לבו לטהר נפשו מטומאות הנפשות שהן מחשבות האון
ודעות הרעות, Vechen mi shekiven libo letaher nafsho mitumos hanafshos shehen machshovos
ha'aven vedi'os hara'os, once he decides in his
heart to separate from those things and brings
his soul into the waters of דעת, Da'as, הרי
זה טהור, Harei zeh tahor, he is pure. The fast day
is our opportunity to submerge our minds in
the truth of our relationship with the רבונו
של עולם. Ribono Shel Olam. It is not just a day
of not eating; it is a day of
thinking, a day of changing our דעת. Da'as. As
שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech says in קהלת, Koheles, בכל עת יהיו
בגדיך לבנים. Bechol eis yihyu vegadecha levanim. Let our thoughts and our
character always be in a state of purity
through the immersion in the waters of the
Torah. In today's lecture we're going to be
discussing the concept of קדושה. kedushah The concept of
קדושה kedushah or holiness is often misunderstood. We think
of it as something otherworldly, something removed from
our daily lives. But the תורה Torah tells us
קדושים תהיו, kedoshim tihyu, you shall be holy. This is
a מצוה for everyone, not just for the
צדיקים tzadikim or the people living in a ישיבה.
yeshiva. The רמבן Ramban in his commentary on the
תורה Torah explains what קדושה kedushah really means. He uses
the famous phrase נבל ברשות התורה, naval b'reshus haTorah, a degenerate
within the permissions of the Law. What does
this mean? It means a person could eat
kosher meat, drink kosher wine, and follow all
the technical rules of שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, but still
be a disgusting human being. They are technically
following the rules, but they are missing the
spirit. קדושה kedushah means to be separate, to elevate.
It means even the things that are permitted
to us, we do with a sense of
purpose and restraint. It's not just about avoiding
the אסור, assur, the forbidden. It's about how we
handle the מותר, muttar, the permitted. We see this
in the context of the משכן, mishkan, the sanctuary.
The vessels, the כלים, keilim, were holy because they
were set aside for a divine purpose. In
the same way, we make ourselves holy when
we set aside our physical desires for a
higher goal. This is what we call עבודת
השם. avodas Hashem. In the פרשה parsha of קדושים, Kedoshim, we have
many different מצוות. mitzvos. Some are between man and
God, בין אדם למקום, bein adam l'makom, and some are between
man and his fellow man, בין אדם לחבירו.
bein adam l'chavero. Why are they mixed together?
Because true קדושה kedushah encompasses both. You can't be
holy if you are dishonest in business or
if you don't care about the poor. The
תורה Torah says, ואהבת לרעך כמוך, v'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha, love your neighbor
as yourself. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says this is a
כלל גדול בתורה, klal gadol baTorah, a great principle in the
Law. This is part of the command to
be holy. Holiness isn't just about being in
a בית מדרש Beis Medrash all day. It's about how
you treat the waiter, how you talk to
your spouse, and how you conduct yourself in
the שוק, shuk, the marketplace. There's a beautiful idea
from the שפת אמת. Sfas Emes. He says that ה'
Hashem didn't just give us the command to
be holy, He also gave us the power
to be holy. The phrase קדושים תהיו kedoshim tihyu is
not just a command, it's a promise. If
you try, ה' Hashem will help you achieve that
level of holiness. How do we start? The
first step is awareness. Before we eat, before
we speak, before we act, we stop for
a second and ask, is this bringing more
קדושה kedushah, into the world? Is this an act
of קידוש ה'? Kiddush Hashem? Or is it just fulfilling
a physical urge? This doesn't mean we have
to be סגפנים, sigfanim, ascetics who fast all day.
Judaism doesn't believe in that. We believe in
taking the עולם הזה, olam hazeh, this world, and making
it holy. When we eat a meal and
say a ברכה bracha with intention, we are elevating
that food. We are turning a physical act
into a spiritual one. This is the ultimate
goal of the יהודי, Yehudi, the Jew. To build
a דירה בתחתונים, dirah b'tachtonim, a dwelling place for ה'
Hashem in this lower world. We do this
through our מצוות mitzvos and through our character, our
מדות. middos. Let's take this message to heart. Let's
strive to be a bit more mindful, a
bit more elevated. Let's fulfill the call of
קדושים תהיו kedoshim tihyu in every aspect of our lives.
Thank you for listening. Have a wonderful week
and a שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom. We learn in מסכת
אבות, Masechet Avot, הוי עז כנמר, Hevei az kanamer, be bold as
a leopard, וקל כנשר, v'kal kanesher, and light as an
eagle, to do the will of your Father
in heaven. This teaches us that in our
עבודת השם, Avodat Hashem, we need to use all our
different character traits, even the ones that might
seem negative, like boldness or aggression, and channel
them for the good. This is what it
means to serve השם Hashem with your whole heart,
בכל לבבך, b'chol levavecha, with both your יצר הטוב Yetzer Hatov and
your יצר הרע. Yetzer Hara. Everything in this world was
created for the כבוד Kavod of הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Hakadosh Baruch Hu, and our job is to
find the holiness in every single thing. By
taking those traits that we might think are
mundane or even base and elevating them to
the service of the בורא, Borei, we are fulfilling
the purpose of creation. As it says, בכל
דרכיך דעהו, B'chol derachecha da'ehu, in all your ways, know Him.
This is not just when we are learning
תורה Torah or praying, but in every aspect of
our lives, our work, our interactions with others,
even when we eat or sleep. Every moment
is an opportunity for דבקות, Dveikus, for connecting to
the infinite. Good evening, everyone. We are approaching
the high holiday of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. One of
the most central parts of the ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah service is the blowing of the
שופר. shofar. There is a beautiful story told about
the great רבי, Rebbe, רב Levi Yitzchak of Berditchev.
Before the שופר shofar blowing, he would look for
someone to blow the שופר shofar for the congregation.
One year, a young man came to him
and said, "רבי, Rebbe, I want to blow the
שופר." shofar. The רבי Rebbe asked him, "What intentions, what
כוונות, kavanot, do you have when you blow the
שופר?" shofar? The young man began to recite all
the deep, mystical כוונות kavanot from the אריז"ל. Arizal. The
רבי Rebbe said, "No, that's not what I'm looking
for." Another man came and the רבי Rebbe asked
him the same question. The man started crying and said, "רבי, Rebbe,
I have four daughters to marry off and I have no money.
When I blow the שופר, shofar, I just cry out to השם
Hashem to help me." The Berditchever said, "You will be our בעל
תוקע." baal tokeiah. Have a wonderful evening. Hi everyone. This week's פרשה
Parsha is פרשת בא. Parshat Bo. In the beginning of the פרשה,
Parsha, the תורה Torah says, ויאמר ה' אל משה בא אל פרעה.
Vayomer Hashem el Moshe bo el Paro. ה' Hashem tells משה, Moshe,
"Come to Pharaoh." And the זוהר Zohar asks a famous question. Usually
the word לך lech is used when someone is told to go
somewhere. לך Lech means "go." Why does the תורה use the word
בא, bo, which means "come"? This implies that ה' Hashem was already
there, as if He was saying to משה, Moshe, "Come to me,
because I am already in the palace of Pharaoh." This teaches us
a very powerful lesson. Even in the darkest places, even in the
palace of the wicked Pharaoh, ה' Hashem is there. We are never
alone. No matter what challenges we face, no matter how difficult the
situation, we have to remember בא אל פרעה bo el Paro come
to Pharaoh because ה' Hashem is already there waiting for us. This
gives us the strength to face any challenge and to know that
we can always find ה', Hashem, even in the most unlikely places.
Have a wonderful שבת. Shabbat Welcome back everybody. We are on דף
ל"ח עמוד א. Daf Lamed Chet Amud Aleph. We're learning the second
פרק Perek of מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, titled במה מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin.
The משנה Mishna. lists the different oils and wicks that may or
may not
be
used
for
the
שבת
Shabbat
lights.
We
discussed
how
one
must
prepare
the נר Ner
properly
before שבת Shabbat. begins
to
ensure a
peaceful
and
beautiful
שבת.
Now
we
will
see
the
גמרא
Gemara
on
this
משנה.
We
are
looking
at
מסכת
יומא
Masechet
Yoma
today
on
דף
פו.
daf
peh
vav.
The
גמרא
Gemara
says
גדולה
תשובה,
gedolah
teshuvah,
great
is
repentance,
שמגעת עד
כיסא
הכבוד,
shemaga'at
ad
kisei
hakavod,
that
it reaches
until the
Throne
of
Glory. This is
learned
from
the
פסוק
pasuk
in
הושע
Hoshea
that
says
שובה
ישראל
עד
ה'
אלוהיך, shuvah Yisrael ad Hashem Elokecha, return
O
Israel
unto
the
Lord
your
God.
The
use
of
the
word
עד,
which
means
until,
suggests
that
it reaches
the
very
presence
of
God.
The
גמרא
Gemara
continues
with
another
דרשה
drasha
from
רבי
לוי
Rabbi
Levi
who
says
גדולה תשובה שמביאה
רפואה
לעולם, gedolah teshuvah shemevia refuah la'olam, great is
repentance
for
it
brings healing to the
world,
as
it
says ארפא משובתם אוהבם נדבה,
erpa meshuvatam ohavam
nedavah, I
will
heal
their backsliding, I will
love
them
freely.
We
see
from here
the incredible power
that
a
בעל
תשובה
ba'al
teshuvah
has.
It's
not
just
about
fixing
the
past,
it's about
a
total
transformation.
The
גמרא
then asks a
contradiction.
In
one
place
it
says
שובו
בנים
שובבים,
shuvu
banim
shovavim,
return
you
wayward
children, which suggests
even
when
they
are wayward they are
called
children.
But
then it says כי
אנכי
בעלתי בכם.
ki
anochi ba'alti bachem. The
resolution the גמרא gives
is
כאן מאהבה כאן
מיראה. kan me-ahavah kan mi-yirah. When
a
person returns
out
of love, he is
called a child.
When a person
returns out of fear, the relationship is different. This leads
us to the famous יסוד yesod that
for
one who does תשובה
מאהבה, teshuvah me-ahavah, his זדונות, zedonot, his intentional
sins, נעשו
לו כזכויות, na'asu lo kizchuyot, become
like merits. But
for one
who does תשובה מיראה, teshuvah mi-yirah, his
זדונות zedonot only become like
שגגות, shgagot, unintentional
sins.
This means that the motivation of the heart changes the very
nature of the
past
action. If the past action
leads you to
a
deeper
love
of
God,
then
that action
itself is transformed into something positive. This is the
beauty
of the system of תשובה teshuvah that
הקדוש
ברוך
הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu gave
us. It allows us to
not just move
forward
but
to actually fix and elevate everything that came before. As
the מדרש midrash says,
return seven
times,
שוב
שבעה, shuv shivah,
and
each
time you
will
reach a higher level of
קדושה, kedushah holiness.
Each level
brings a
person
closer
to the source, allowing for
a
complete
purification of the soul.
Thus, the
process
of
returning
is not a single event but a
continuous journey
of
growth.
This
explains
why
the גמרא
places
such
emphasis
on
the
different
motivations,
as the
depth
of one's return
dictates
the
extent of the
spiritual repair
achieved.
One
should always
strive
for a
return
based on
love,
as that has
the
power to turn
even
the darkest moments of the past into light.
We are
entering
the
month of
כסלו.
Kislev.
כסלו
Kislev
contains
the
letters
ס Samech and
ל,
which
stands
for
סיעתא
דשמיא.
Siyata
Di'shmaya.
Help
from
heaven.
We must
realize
that all
of
our
success
comes
from
the
סיעתא
דשמיא
Siyata
Di'shmaya
of
השם.
Hashem.
Like
the
miracles
of
חנוכה,
Chanukah,
it
was
all
from
השם. Hashem. Let's
have
בטחון
Bitachon
and אמונה
Emunah
as
we
go through this month.
חודש טוב. Chodesh Tov. It
starts
with
the word שיר Shir and not מזמור Mizmor because
this
is the song
for the Jewish people
for all of history including
that
which
we don't
understand.
And
at the end
of
פסח,
Pesach,
in fact at the end
of
time,
we're going
to see
that
even those
things
which
were
only
שיר, Shir, things
we
didn't understand, they also turn into a
מזמור, Mizmor, things that have their place,
things
that
are melody
and
rhythm
we see how
they fit into the whole song. This
is
why
we
read
שיר
השירים
Shir
Hashirim
right
before
שביעי
של
פסח.
Shvii
Shel
Pesach.
The
mistake
of
קורח
Korach
was thinking
that
equality means
uniformity,
that
if we are all
holy,
we
all
must
do the same thing. But
true קדושה
comes
from
recognizing
your unique
role
and
fulfilling it
with humility.
That
is
the
lesson
of
the
מחלוקת
machloket
of
קורח.
Korach.
It's
a
warning
against
the
type
of
ego
that
seeks
to
blur
the
lines
of
the
sacred
order
that
God
established.
In
מסכת
ברכות,
Masechet
Berachot,
we
find
a
beautiful
piece
of
advice
on
how
to
improve
our תפילה. tefillah. The
גמרא
says that
a person
should
always
check
themselves before they
stand up
to
pray.
Are
you
in
the
right
frame
of
mind?
Are
you
focused?
The חסידים הראשונים, Chassidim HaRishonim, the early pious ones,
used
to
wait an
entire
hour
before starting
their שמונה
עשרה.
Shemoneh
Esrei.
Why?
To
get
their
hearts
ready.
They
understood
that
תפילה
tefillah
isn't just
about saying words;
it's
about
עבודה
שבלב, avodah she'balev, the service of
the
heart.
If the
heart
isn't
there,
the
words
are
just
sounds.
As
the
רמב"ם
Rambam
explains,
תפילה
בלא
כוונה
אינה
תפילה,
tefillah
belo
kavanah
einah
tefillah,
prayer
without intention
is
not
truly
prayer.
So
today,
before
you
start
your
שחרית
Shacharit
or
מנחה,
Mincha,
take
just one
minute. Just one
minute
to
think
about
who
you
are talking
to.
Standing
before
the
מלך
מלכי
המלכים,
Melech
Malchei
HaMelachim,
the
King
of
all
kings.
That
one
minute
of
הכנה,
hachanah,
of
preparation,
will
change your whole experience.
It
will
turn
your
prayer
from
a
burden
into
a real
connection.
Let's
try
to
find
that
moment
of שקט,
sheket,
of
silence,
and
prepare
our
hearts.
שיהיה
לכם יום
טוב,
She'yehiye
lachem
yom
tov,
have
a
wonderful
day.
Alright,
so
let's
continue
with
the ענין
inyan
of prayer.
We
find
in
the
גמרא
in
מסכת
ברכות
Masechet
Berakhot
that
the
times
for
the
תפילות tefillot were
established
based
on
the
different
times
of
the day.
Specifically, the morning
prayer,
known
as
שחרית,
Shacharit,
corresponds to
the
morning
תמיד
Tamid
offering
in
the
בית
המקדש.
Beit
HaMikdash.
And
the
afternoon
prayer,
מנחה,
Mincha,
is
linked to
the
afternoon
offering.
It's
important
to recognize
that
even
though
we
no
longer
have the
קרבנות,
korbanot,
our
תפילה tefillah serves
as
a
replacement, or
at
least
a
way
to maintain that connection,
as
the
פסוק
says,
ונשלמה פרים שפתינו. unishalma parim sefateinu. This
concept
of
תפילות
כנגד
תמידין
תיקנום
tefillot
keneged
temidin
tiknum
is
fundamental
to
our
understanding of
the daily
schedule.
The
רמב"ם Rambam, explains
that
every
physical thing
in
this
world
is
composed of two components: חומר
Chomer
and צורה.
Tzurah.
חומר
Chomer
refers
to the matter,
the
physical
substance, while צורה
Tzurah
refers
to
the
form.
However,
it's crucial to
understand
that
צורה
Tzurah
does
not
mean
shape.
In
the
language
of
the
רמב"ם,
Rambam
the
shape of
an
object
is
a
מקרה,
Mikre,
an accidental or
secondary
property.
The
צורה Tzurah is the
essence
of the
thing,
the
quality
that
makes
it
what
is.
For
example,
for
a
human
being,
the
חומר
Chomer
is
the
גוף,
Guf,
the
physical
body,
and
the
צורה
Tzurah
is
the
נפש,
Nefesh,
the
soul,
specifically
the
שכל,
Sechel,
the
human
intellect.
As
long
as
the
צורה
Tzurah
is
attached
to
the
חומר,
Chomer,
the
object
is
called
an
אדם, Adam, a
human
being.
But
the
moment
צורה Tzurah departs,
what
remains
is only the
חומר,
Chomer,
which is
no longer
an
אדם
Adam
but
simply
matter.
This is how the רמב"ם explains
the relationship between the
body and
the
soul.
The
soul
is
the
צורה,
Tzurah,
the
essence,
and
the
body
is
the
חומר,
Chomer,
the
matter.